[
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Administrative Structure",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following birds is the state bird of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Great Indian Bustard",
          "Kaleej Pheasant",
          "Monal",
          "Pigeon"
        ],
        "answer": "Monal"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "In which district is the Askote Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
        "options": ["Almora", "Chamoli", "Uttarkashi", "Pithoragarh"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "What is the favorite food of the state bird Monal?",
        "options": ["Chickpea", "Potato", "Gravel", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Potato"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "What is 'Kanchula Khark' in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Herb Research Center",
          "Software Center",
          "Musk Deer Conservation and Breeding Center",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Musk Deer Conservation and Breeding Center"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "How many species of the state flower 'Brahmakamal' are found in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["26", "39", "24", "410"],
        "answer": "24"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "What is the flowering time of the state tree 'Buransh'?",
        "options": [
          "February to April",
          "May to July",
          "August to October",
          "November to January"
        ],
        "answer": "February to April"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "How many districts are there in the state of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["15", "12", "13", "10"],
        "answer": "13"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following Legislative Assembly seats is reserved for Scheduled Tribes?",
        "options": [
          "Khatima Legislative Assembly seat",
          "Chakrata Legislative Assembly seat",
          "Pindar Legislative Assembly seat",
          "Dharchula Legislative Assembly seat"
        ],
        "answer": "Chakrata Legislative Assembly seat"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Two statements are given below. Assertion (A): The Uttarakhand State Legislature has a total of 70 members. Reason (R): The state has a bicameral legislature. In the context of the above, which one of the following is correct?",
        "options": [
          "Both and (R) are true, and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
          "Both and (R) are true, but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
          "is true, but (R) is false.",
          "is false, but (R) is true."
        ],
        "answer": "is true, but (R) is false."
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Which is the westernmost district of the state?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Uttarkashi", "Haridwar", "Pithoragarh"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "In Uttarakhand, a village council (Gram Sabha) is established by -",
        "options": [
          "The Divisional Commissioner",
          "The District Magistrate of the district",
          "The District Panchayat",
          "The State Government"
        ],
        "answer": "The State Government"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "In how many cities of the state are there Municipal Corporations?",
        "options": ["1", "3", "8", "9"],
        "answer": "9"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "The city head of a Municipal Corporation in Uttarakhand -",
        "options": [
          "Is appointed by the State Government.",
          "Is nominated by the Governor.",
          "Is elected by the local people.",
          "Is elected by the council members."
        ],
        "answer": "Is elected by the local people."
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "The commission formed by the state government for the selection of a permanent capital for the state of Uttarakhand is -",
        "options": [
          "Pant Commission",
          "Limnah Commission",
          "Dixit Commission",
          "Banerjee Commission"
        ],
        "answer": "Dixit Commission"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "The actual head of the state executive is -",
        "options": ["Governor", "Cabinet", "Chief Minister", "Chief Secretary"],
        "answer": "Chief Minister"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "What percentage of horizontal reservation has been provided for women in all categories of services in the state of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["5%", "10%", "30%", "20%"],
        "answer": "30%"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Uttarakhand is which state of India?",
        "options": ["22nd", "11th", "27th", "28th"],
        "answer": "27th"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "What is the total number of judges, including the Chief Justice, in the State High Court?",
        "options": ["17", "15", "13", "11"],
        "answer": "11"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Which of the following is not in the Garhwal Mandal?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Rudraprayag", "Bageshwar", "Pauri"],
        "answer": "Bageshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Who was the first Chief Minister of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "N.D. Tiwari",
          "Bhagat Singh Koshyari",
          "Nityanand Swami",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Nityanand Swami"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "What is the limit of women's reservation in Panchayats under the Panchayati Raj Amendment Act 2008?",
        "options": ["30%", "33%", "40%", "50%"],
        "answer": "50%"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Up to what altitude are Monal birds found?",
        "options": [
          "800-9000 feet",
          "8000-10000 feet",
          "8000-14000 feet",
          "8000-20000 feet"
        ],
        "answer": "8000-20000 feet"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Which deity is Brahmakamal flower offered to?",
        "options": ["Ram", "Krishna", "Shiva", "Vishnu"],
        "answer": "Shiva"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Which new department was created in the state in 2011?",
        "options": [
          "Good Governance, Eradication of Corruption and Public Service",
          "Sports and Tourism",
          "Disaster Management",
          "Higher Education Commission"
        ],
        "answer": "Good Governance, Eradication of Corruption and Public Service"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Who was the first Deputy Speaker of the State Legislative Assembly?",
        "options": [
          "Vijaya Barthwal",
          "Amrita Rawat",
          "Veena Maharana",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Vijaya Barthwal"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "What is the second official language of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Urdu", "Sanskrit", "English", "Punjabi"],
        "answer": "Sanskrit"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Match the following lists and choose the correct answer:\nHawalbagh  - 1. Uttarkashi\nGunda      - 2. Nainital\nOkhalkanda - 3. Haridwar\nKhanapur   - 4. Almora",
        "options": [
          "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4",
          "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2",
          "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3",
          "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1"
        ],
        "answer": "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Which districts of Uttarakhand have the largest and smallest areas respectively?",
        "options": [
          "Chamoli and Rudraprayag",
          "Chamoli and Champawat",
          "Uttarkashi and Rudraprayag",
          "Uttarkashi and Champawat"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi and Champawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Which is the correct sequence of districts in the state in descending order of area?",
        "options": [
          "Uttarkashi, Chamoli, Pauri, Pithoragarh, Nainital",
          "Uttarkashi, Chamoli, Pithoragarh, Pauri, Nainital",
          "Chamoli, Uttarkashi, Pithoragarh, Pauri, Nainital",
          "Chamoli, Pithoragarh, Uttarkashi, Nainital, Pauri"
        ],
        "answer": "Chamoli, Uttarkashi, Pithoragarh, Pauri, Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Out of the total 5 Lok Sabha seats in the state, how many are reserved for Scheduled Castes (SC)?",
        "options": ["1", "2", "3", "4"],
        "answer": "1"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "What is the reservation percentage for SC, ST, and OBC in state services?",
        "options": [
          "19%, 4%, 14%",
          "19%, 5%, 15%",
          "17%, 5%, 13%",
          "18%, 4%, 14%"
        ],
        "answer": "19%, 4%, 14%"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "What is the reservation percentage for freedom fighters and state movement activists in state services?",
        "options": ["3% & 10%", "2% & 10%", "1% & 10%", "5% & 10%"],
        "answer": "2% & 10%"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "What is the reservation percentage for ex-servicemen and sportspersons in the state?",
        "options": ["5% & 2%", "5% & 3%", "5% & 4%", "4% & 4%"],
        "answer": "5% & 4%"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "In which year were the districts Rudraprayag, Champawat, and Bageshwar created?",
        "options": ["1995", "1996", "1997", "1998"],
        "answer": "1997"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Which district has the highest number of villages?",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Dehradun", "Pauri"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of Garhwal Mandal?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Pauri", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "When was the first elected Legislative Assembly formed in the state?",
        "options": ["2000", "2001", "2002", "2003"],
        "answer": "2002"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "Which of the following districts and tehsils is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Tehri - Dhansali",
          "Dehradun - Vikasnagar",
          "Chamoli - Mori",
          "Pithoragarh - Berinag"
        ],
        "answer": "Chamoli - Mori"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Which of the following districts and blocks is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Almora - Salt",
          "Haridwar - Garud",
          "Uttarkashi - Purola",
          "Chamoli - Tharali"
        ],
        "answer": "Haridwar - Garud"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Which of the following districts has the largest area?",
        "options": ["Champawat", "Rudraprayag", "Bageshwar", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Who was the first female Governor of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Smt. Kamla Beniwal",
          "Smt. Mridula Sinha",
          "Smt. Margaret Alva",
          "Smt. Sheila Dikshit"
        ],
        "answer": "Smt. Margaret Alva"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "To whom does the State Public Service Commission submit its annual report?",
        "options": [
          "Chief Minister",
          "Home Minister",
          "Governor",
          "Chief Justice"
        ],
        "answer": "Governor"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "What is the maximum number of ministers allowed in the Uttarakhand Council of Ministers?",
        "options": ["10", "12", "11", "15"],
        "answer": "12"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "How many seats are reserved for Scheduled Tribes in the Uttarakhand Legislative Assembly?",
        "options": ["01", "02", "03", "04"],
        "answer": "02"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "What is the state flower of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Brahmakamal", "Buransh", "Rose", "Lotus"],
        "answer": "Brahmakamal"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Who was the first Director General of Police (DGP) of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "G.C. Pandey",
          "B.S. Siddhu",
          "Sanjay Gunjyal",
          "Ashok Kant Saran"
        ],
        "answer": "Ashok Kant Saran"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "When was the name of Uttaranchal changed to Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "January 1, 2007",
          "May 7, 2002",
          "December 22, 1999",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "January 1, 2007"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "'Monal' is the state bird of which state?",
        "options": [
          "Jammu and Kashmir",
          "Himachal Pradesh",
          "Uttarakhand",
          "and (c)"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarakhand"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Who was the first Governor of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Nityanand Swami",
          "Bhagat Singh Koshyari",
          "Surjit Singh Barnala",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Surjit Singh Barnala"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "How many development blocks are there in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["94", "95", "96", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "95"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "What is the state sport of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Kho-Kho", "Football", "Hockey", "Badminton"],
        "answer": "Football"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "Which of the following is not true?",
        "options": [
          "The state tree of Uttarakhand is Buransh.",
          "The state sport of Uttarakhand is Badminton.",
          "The state bird of Uttarakhand is Monal.",
          "The state animal of Uttarakhand is Musk Deer."
        ],
        "answer": "The state sport of Uttarakhand is Badminton."
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "How many Lok Sabha seats are there in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["5", "7", "3", "13"],
        "answer": "5"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "How many Rajya Sabha seats are there in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["5", "2", "3", "7"],
        "answer": "3"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Where is the recognized High Court of Uttarakhand located?",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Pauri", "Nainital", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "How many districts of Kumaon Mandal touch the boundary of Garhwal Mandal?",
        "options": ["5", "2", "3", "4"],
        "answer": "4"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "Who was the first Chief Secretary of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Shatrughan Singh",
          "Rakesh Sharma",
          "Ajay Vikram Singh",
          "Subhash Kumar"
        ],
        "answer": "Ajay Vikram Singh"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "How many districts are there in Kumaon Mandal?",
        "options": ["7", "5", "6", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "6"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Who appoints the Advocate General for the state?",
        "options": [
          "President of India",
          "Vice President of India",
          "Chief Justice of the State",
          "Governor of the State"
        ],
        "answer": "Governor of the State"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "Who elects the Mayor of Municipal Corporations in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Members of Lok Sabha",
          "Members of the State Legislative Assembly",
          "Directly by the public",
          "Members of the Corporation"
        ],
        "answer": "Directly by the public"
      },
      {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "When was the 'Kaushik Committee' formed?",
        "options": ["Year 1994", "Year 2000", "Year 1971", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Year 1994"
      },
      {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "What is the maximum number of ministers, including the Chief Minister, allowed in the State Council of Ministers?",
        "options": ["10", "12", "14", "9"],
        "answer": "12"
      },
      {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "When was President's Rule imposed in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "March 27, 2016",
          "March 24, 2016",
          "March 20, 2016",
          "March 30, 2016"
        ],
        "answer": "March 27, 2016"
      },
      {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "Who was the sixth Governor of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "B.L. Joshi",
          "Dr. Aziz Qureshi",
          "Dr. Krishna Kant Paul",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Krishna Kant Paul"
      },
      {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "Who was the Speaker of the first elected Legislative Assembly of the state?",
        "options": [
          "Prakash Pant",
          "Harbans Kapoor",
          "Govind Singh Kunjwal",
          "Yashpal Arya"
        ],
        "answer": "Yashpal Arya"
      },
      {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "In which year was Nainital made the summer capital of U.P.?",
        "options": ["1958", "1927", "1963", "1962"],
        "answer": "1962"
      },
      {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "Which Legislative Assembly seat is reserved for Scheduled Tribes?",
        "options": ["Khatima", "Laksar", "Nanakmatta", "Dharchula"],
        "answer": "Nanakmatta"
      },
      {
        "id": 68,
        "question": "Which is the state tree of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Sal", "Teak", "Buransh", "Brahmakamal"],
        "answer": "Buransh"
      },
      {
        "id": 69,
        "question": "On what date did the state of Uttarakhand come into existence?",
        "options": ["9-11-2000", "9-11-2001", "11-11-2001", "5-11-2001"],
        "answer": "9-11-2000"
      },
      {
        "id": 70,
        "question": "How many seats were there in the undivided Uttar Pradesh Legislative Assembly for Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["20", "21", "22", "23"],
        "answer": "22"
      },
      {
        "id": 71,
        "question": "Which Legislative Assembly seat is reserved for Scheduled Tribes in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Purola", "Khatima", "Nanakmatta", "Jhabreda"],
        "answer": "Nanakmatta"
      },
      {
        "id": 72,
        "question": "On what date was the Uttar Pradesh Reorganization Act signed by the President for the creation of Uttarakhand state?",
        "options": [
          "August 1, 2000",
          "August 5, 2000",
          "August 28, 2000",
          "August 30, 2000"
        ],
        "answer": "August 1, 2000"
      },
      {
        "id": 73,
        "question": "Which committee rejected Gairsain as the permanent capital of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Kaushik Commission",
          "Koshiyari Commission",
          "Dixit Commission",
          "Rautela Commission"
        ],
        "answer": "Dixit Commission"
      },
      {
        "id": 74,
        "question": "What percentage of horizontal reservation is provided for women in government services in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["5%", "10%", "30%", "33%"],
        "answer": "30%"
      },
      {
        "id": 75,
        "question": "Who was the pioneer of voluntary 'Chakbandi' in the Yamuna Valley?",
        "options": [
          "Kedar Singh Rawat",
          "Yudhveer Singh Rawat",
          "Prahlad Singh Rawat",
          "Late. Rajendra Singh Rawat"
        ],
        "answer": "Late. Rajendra Singh Rawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 76,
        "question": "Where is the Uttarakhand Judicial and Legal Academy located?",
        "options": ["Kotdwar", "Bhowali", "Lansdowne", "Bageshwar"],
        "answer": "Bhowali"
      },
      {
        "id": 77,
        "question": "Which tax is levied by the Gram Panchayat?",
        "options": [
          "Goods and Services Tax",
          "Tax on local fairs",
          "Customs Duty",
          "Land Revenue"
        ],
        "answer": "Tax on local fairs"
      },
      {
        "id": 78,
        "question": "When was the reservation for women in Panchayati Raj in Uttarakhand increased to 50 percent?",
        "options": ["2006", "2007", "2008", "2009"],
        "answer": "2008"
      },
      {
        "id": 79,
        "question": "Two statements are given below. One is labeled as assertion and the other as reason (R). Answer using the codes.",
        "options": [
          "Both and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
          "Both and (R) are true, but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
          "is true, but (R) is false.",
          "is false, but (R) is true."
        ],
        "answer": "is true, but (R) is false."
      },
      {
        "id": 80,
        "question": "Which is the first Municipal Corporation to be established entirely in a mountainous area in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Karnprayag", "Uttarkashi", "Srinagar", "Augustmuni"],
        "answer": "Srinagar"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Physical Structure, Climate, and Natural Disasters",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Which district has the largest area in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Dehradun", "Uttarkashi", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Based on terrain configuration, rock formations, and elevation, how many geographical regions can Uttarakhand be divided into?",
        "options": ["15", "12", "8", "10"],
        "answer": "8"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following earthquakes had the highest intensity?",
        "options": [
          "Capkot 1958",
          "Dharchula 1980",
          "Chamoli 1999",
          "Uttarkashi 1991"
        ],
        "answer": "Chamoli 1999"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "In which part of Uttarakhand are 'Pataltod' or 'Source Wells' found?",
        "options": [
          "Bhabar region",
          "Terai region",
          "Shivalik Hills",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Terai region"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a district of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Bageshwar", "Champawat", "Rudraprayag", "Rudrapur"],
        "answer": "Rudrapur"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following districts of Uttarakhand shares a border with Nepal?",
        "options": [
          "Pauri Garhwal",
          "Pithoragarh",
          "Uttarkashi",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is the highest mountain peak in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Trishul", "Kamet", "Kedarnath", "Nanda Devi"],
        "answer": "Nanda Devi"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Which place in Uttarakhand is known as 'Queen of Hills'?",
        "options": ["Mussoorie", "Nainital", "Almora", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "What are Kingri-Bingri, Neeti, Sail-Shal, and Dharma?",
        "options": ["Mountains", "Lakes", "Passes", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Passes"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Where are the Nahan mountain ranges located in the state?",
        "options": [
          "Near Haldwani",
          "Near Tehri",
          "Near Lansdowne",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Near Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Which pass connects the Darma and Vyas valleys in the state?",
        "options": ["Unta", "Jyantya", "Sinla", "Ramal"],
        "answer": "Sinla"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Trade between Tibet and Nepal takes place through which district's passes?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Pithoragarh", "Joshimath", "Lansdowne"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Which mountain range is the highest among the following mountains of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Trishul", "Doonagiri", "Nandadevi", "Kamet"],
        "answer": "Nandadevi"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Badrinath is located in?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Rudraprayag", "Tehri", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Which is the highest snow-covered mountain peak in the state?",
        "options": ["Nanda Devi", "Kamet", "Changori", "Trishul"],
        "answer": "Nanda Devi"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Valley of Flowers is located in?",
        "options": [
          "Shivalik region",
          "Greater Himalayan region",
          "Middle Himalayan region",
          "Doon Himalayan region"
        ],
        "answer": "Greater Himalayan region"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "What are 'Doon' called in the state?",
        "options": [
          "River valleys",
          "Structural valleys",
          "Alpine grasslands",
          "Narrow valleys"
        ],
        "answer": "Structural valleys"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Which area of Uttarakhand comes under the highly vulnerable zone for landslides?",
        "options": [
          "Middle Himalayan region",
          "Greater Himalayan region",
          "Outer Himalayan region",
          "Lakeshore regions"
        ],
        "answer": "Middle Himalayan region"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Which pass connects Bageshwar and Pithoragarh?",
        "options": ["Shringkanth", "Trail Pass", "Sinla", "Barahoti"],
        "answer": "Trail Pass"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Which pass connects Uttarkashi and Tibet?",
        "options": ["Darma", "Neeti", "Thagala", "Kingri-Bingri"],
        "answer": "Thagala"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Where is the Main Central Thrust line located in the state?",
        "options": [
          "North of the Greater Himalayas",
          "South of the Outer Himalayas",
          "Between the Middle and Outer Himalayas",
          "Between the Greater and Middle Himalayas"
        ],
        "answer": "Between the Greater and Middle Himalayas"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "According to scientists, what is the main reason for most earthquakes in the Himalayan region (Uttarakhand)?",
        "options": [
          "Plate tectonics",
          "Presence of faults",
          "Construction of tube wells",
          "Both a and b"
        ],
        "answer": "Both a and b"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Which of the following peaks is not located in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Nandakot", "Chaukhamba", "Kula Kangri", "Chunagiri"],
        "answer": "Kula Kangri"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "From the perspective of natural disasters, Uttarakhand falls in which zone?",
        "options": [
          "Zone 1 and 2",
          "Zone 2 and 3",
          "Zone 3 and 4",
          "Zone 4 and 5"
        ],
        "answer": "Zone 4 and 5"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Which region in the state receives the highest rainfall?",
        "options": [
          "Doon region",
          "Outer Himalayan region",
          "Middle Himalayan region",
          "Greater Himalayan region"
        ],
        "answer": "Outer Himalayan region"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Which place in the state has the highest average annual rainfall?",
        "options": [
          "Mussoorie (Dehradun)",
          "Narendra Nagar (Tehri)",
          "Kotdwar (Pauri)",
          "Gangotri (Uttarkashi)"
        ],
        "answer": "Narendra Nagar (Tehri)"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Which districts of Uttarakhand have completely internal boundaries?",
        "options": [
          "Tehri-Rudraprayag",
          "Rudraprayag-Bageshwar",
          "Bageshwar-Almora",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Which district has the longest international border?",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Champawat"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a hill station in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Mussoorie", "Dehradun", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Which of the following towns in the state are located in the Terai region?",
        "options": [
          "Aurangabad-Jwalapur",
          "Sitarganj-Bajpur",
          "Kashipur-Khatima",
          "All"
        ],
        "answer": "All"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "Which fault line separates the Lesser Himalayas and the Greater Himalayas in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Main Boundary Thrust",
          "Trans-Himalayan Fault",
          "Main Central Thrust",
          "Almora Thrust"
        ],
        "answer": "Main Central Thrust"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "What is the approximate height of the Shivalik ranges?",
        "options": ["850-1200m", "750-100m", "750-1500m", "750-1300m"],
        "answer": "750-1300m"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "What is the total area of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "53,483 sq km",
          "60,480 sq km",
          "55,483 sq km",
          "65,480 sq km"
        ],
        "answer": "53,483 sq km"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "What is the ancient name of the Shivalik range?",
        "options": [
          "Mainak Parvat",
          "Mandagadhan Parvat",
          "Kailash Parvat",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Mainak Parvat"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Where is 'Mana Pass' located?",
        "options": [
          "Uttar Pradesh",
          "Uttarakhand",
          "Kashmir",
          "Himachal Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarakhand"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "The upper part of Almora district is located in which range?",
        "options": [
          "Greater Himalayas",
          "Shivalik Range",
          "Lesser Himalayas",
          "Trans Himalayas"
        ],
        "answer": "Lesser Himalayas"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Into how many climatic zones is Uttarakhand divided?",
        "options": ["6", "5", "8", "4"],
        "answer": "4"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "The Pamer of Uttarakhand (Dudhatoli Range) is a part of which range?",
        "options": [
          "Shivalik Range",
          "Middle Himalayan Range",
          "Greater Himalayan Range",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Middle Himalayan Range"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "The 'Queen of Hills' (Mussoorie) is part of which range?",
        "options": [
          "Shivalik Range",
          "Middle Himalayan Range",
          "Greater Himalayan Range",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Middle Himalayan Range"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Lipulekh-Pithoragarh",
          "Tungan/Sunjan-Chamoli",
          "Barahoti-Uttarkashi",
          "Trail-Bageshwar"
        ],
        "answer": "Barahoti-Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Which Himalayan range remains mostly snow-covered throughout the year?",
        "options": [
          "Trans Himalayas",
          "Greater Himalayas",
          "Middle Himalayas",
          "Outer Himalayas"
        ],
        "answer": "Greater Himalayas"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Which disaster can have the most devastating impact on the state?",
        "options": ["Earthquake", "Landslide", "Avalanche", "Flood"],
        "answer": "Earthquake"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "The Lesser Himalayas are located between which ranges?",
        "options": [
          "Trans and Greater Himalayas",
          "Shivalik and Greater Himalayas",
          "Trans and Shivalik Himalayas",
          "Shivalik and Outer Himalayas"
        ],
        "answer": "Shivalik and Greater Himalayas"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of the Survey of India located?",
        "options": ["Chandigarh", "Hyderabad", "Dehradun", "Delhi"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "Shringkanth Pass is located between which regions?",
        "options": [
          "Uttarakhand-Uttar Pradesh",
          "Uttarakhand-Himachal Pradesh",
          "Uttarakhand-Tibet",
          "Uttarakhand-Nepal"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarakhand-Himachal Pradesh"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "In which district is the Thangla Pass located?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Uttarkashi", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Consider the following statements and choose the correct answer:",
        "options": [
          "A and B are correct",
          "B and C are correct",
          "A and C are correct",
          "All are correct"
        ],
        "answer": "All are correct"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Which group of districts in Uttarakhand shares an international border?",
        "options": [
          "Champawat, Nainital, Udham Singh Nagar",
          "Pithoragarh, Chamoli, Uttarkashi",
          "Chamoli, Uttarkashi, Rudraprayag",
          "Chamoli, Pithoragarh, Bageshwar"
        ],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh, Chamoli, Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Uttarakhand is located in which part of the Himalayas?",
        "options": [
          "East-Central part",
          "West-Central part",
          "North-Central part",
          "South-Central part"
        ],
        "answer": "West-Central part"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Which district of Uttarakhand is mainly located in the Terai region?",
        "options": ["Udham Singh Nagar", "Dehradun", "Almora", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Udham Singh Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "In which of the following districts of Uttarakhand is the Dunagiri mountain peak located?",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Chamoli", "Almora", "Bageshwar"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "In which of the following districts is Kotadun located?",
        "options": ["Pauri", "Dehradun", "Nainital", "Champawat"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "The natural phenomenon called 'Winter Line' is visible in:",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Mussoorie", "Kausani", "Mana"],
        "answer": "Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a natural boundary of the state?",
        "options": [
          "Kali River in the East",
          "Yamuna River in the West",
          "Tibetan Himalayas in the North",
          "Bhabar-Terai region in the South"
        ],
        "answer": "Yamuna River in the West"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Borasu Pass - Uttarkashi",
          "Barahoti Pass - Uttarkashi",
          "Turjun Pass - Chamoli",
          "Lamkhaga Pass - Uttarkashi"
        ],
        "answer": "Barahoti Pass - Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "How many districts of the state share a border with Uttar Pradesh?",
        "options": ["3", "4", "5", "6"],
        "answer": "3"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "Which is the district with the smallest area in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Champawat", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Almora", "Rudraprayag"],
        "answer": "Champawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "Match the following mountain peaks with their heights (in meters):\nNanda Devi - 1.7817m\nKamet - 2.7756m\nPanchachuli - 3.6904m\nKedarnath - 4.6968m",
        "options": ["A2 B1 C3 D4", "A3 B4 C1 D2", "A1 B2 C3 D4", "A4 B3 C2 D1"],
        "answer": "A3 B4 C1 D2"
      },

      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "What is located between the Nar and Narayan mountains?",
        "options": ["Valley of Flowers", "Joshimath", "Tapovan", "Badrinath"],
        "answer": "Badrinath"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "What are Kingri-Bingri, Neeti, and Mana?",
        "options": ["Passes", "Rivers", "Mountains", "Religious sites"],
        "answer": "Passes"
      },
      {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "Which Himalayan region receives the highest rainfall during the rainy season?",
        "options": [
          "Upper Himalayas",
          "Outer Himalayas",
          "Inner Himalayas",
          "Equal rainfall in all three"
        ],
        "answer": "Outer Himalayas"
      },
      {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "What is the height of the Nandakot mountain peak?",
        "options": ["7138m", "6400m", "6861m", "6320m"],
        "answer": "6861m"
      },
      {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "The slogan 'Save the Himalayas, Save the Country' is associated with:",
        "options": [
          "Bishni Devi",
          "Gauri Devi",
          "Sundarlal Bahuguna",
          "Hemwati Nandan Bahuguna"
        ],
        "answer": "Sundarlal Bahuguna"
      },
      {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "Dehradun's 'Wadia Institute of Himalayan Geology' is related to:",
        "options": ["Music", "Sports", "Medicine", "Geology"],
        "answer": "Geology"
      },
      {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "In which district is 'Nandhaur Dun' located?",
        "options": ["Udham Singh Nagar", "Nainital", "Garhwal", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "On which date is 'Himalayan Day' celebrated in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["September 9", "September 5", "September 15", "October 5"],
        "answer": "September 9"
      },
      {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "When did the water disaster occur in Kedarnath?",
        "options": ["April 2013", "May 2013", "June 2013", "July 2013"],
        "answer": "June 2013"
      },
      {
        "id": 68,
        "question": "Which operation is related to 'Uttarakhand'?",
        "options": [
          "Operation Kedar",
          "Operation Badri",
          "Operation Choti",
          "Operation Surya Hope"
        ],
        "answer": "Operation Surya Hope"
      },
      {
        "id": 69,
        "question": "What percentage of the total area of Uttarakhand is mountainous?",
        "options": ["90", "86", "50", "45"],
        "answer": "86"
      },
      {
        "id": 70,
        "question": "In which district is Barahoti located?",
        "options": ["Rudraprayag", "Pithoragarh", "Chamoli", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 71,
        "question": "Which of the following is called 'Queen of Hills'?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Dhanaulti", "Mussoorie", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 72,
        "question": "Which district of Uttarakhand shares its boundary with seven districts of the state?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Almora", "Pauri Garhwal", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Pauri Garhwal"
      },
      {
        "id": 73,
        "question": "'Lipulekh Pass' is located in:",
        "options": [
          "Uttarkashi district",
          "Chamoli district",
          "Pithoragarh district",
          "Bageshwar district"
        ],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh district"
      },
      {
        "id": 74,
        "question": "When did the cloudburst incident occur in Malpa, Pithoragarh district?",
        "options": [
          "August 17-18, 2002",
          "August 17-18, 1996",
          "August 17-18, 1998",
          "August 17-18, 1999"
        ],
        "answer": "August 17-18, 1998"
      },
      {
        "id": 75,
        "question": "'Doon Valley' is located in which district?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Rishikesh", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 76,
        "question": "What type of climate is found in the Bhabar belt of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Alpine", "Subtropical", "Tropical", "Temperate"],
        "answer": "Subtropical"
      },
      {
        "id": 77,
        "question": "Which of the following passes is not located in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Lipulekh Pass", "Mana Pass", "Sin-La Pass", "Dibsa Pass"],
        "answer": "Dibsa Pass"
      },
      {
        "id": 78,
        "question": "Which of the following passes is used by Mansarovar pilgrims?",
        "options": [
          "Mana Pass",
          "Lipulekh Pass",
          "Nama Pass",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Lipulekh Pass"
      },
      {
        "id": 79,
        "question": "What is the height of the Panchachuli peak above sea level?",
        "options": ["6,806m", "7,120m", "6,904m", "7,456m"],
        "answer": "6,904m"
      },
      {
        "id": 80,
        "question": "'Lampiya Dhura' connects:",
        "options": [
          "Pithoragarh and Tibet",
          "Pithoragarh and Nepal",
          "Pithoragarh and Chamoli",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh and Tibet"
      },
      {
        "id": 81,
        "question": "Which of the following connects 'Shringkanth Pass'?",
        "options": [
          "Pithoragarh-Tibet",
          "Chamoli",
          "Uttarkashi-Himachal Pradesh",
          "Bageshwar-Pithoragarh"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi-Himachal Pradesh"
      },
      {
        "id": 82,
        "question": "Thangla, Dungrila, Nelang, Lamlang are:",
        "options": ["Lakes", "Mountains", "Passes", "Rivers"],
        "answer": "Passes"
      },
      {
        "id": 83,
        "question": "Doonagiri Glacier is located in:",
        "options": [
          "Dehradun district",
          "Pithoragarh district",
          "Uttarkashi district",
          "Chamoli district"
        ],
        "answer": "Chamoli district"
      },
      {
        "id": 84,
        "question": "Which hill station was called 'Switzerland of India' by Mahatma Gandhi?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Mussoorie", "Ranikhet", "Kausani"],
        "answer": "Kausani"
      },
      {
        "id": 85,
        "question": "What is the height of the Kamet peak?",
        "options": ["7138m", "7756m", "7817m", "7272m"],
        "answer": "7756m"
      },
      {
        "id": 86,
        "question": "Which district of Uttarakhand has the largest area?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 87,
        "question": "Which is the longest glacier in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Milam", "Gangotri", "Pindari", "Satopanth"],
        "answer": "Gangotri"
      },
      {
        "id": 88,
        "question": "Which is the second highest peak in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Trishul", "Kamet", "Chaukhamba", "Panchachuli"],
        "answer": "Kamet"
      },
      {
        "id": 89,
        "question": "Which is the easternmost district of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Champawat",
          "Nainital",
          "Udham Singh Nagar",
          "Pithoragarh"
        ],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 90,
        "question": "How many districts of the state share an international border?",
        "options": ["3", "4", "5", "6"],
        "answer": "3"
      },
      {
        "id": 91,
        "question": "Which of the following is the highest peak?",
        "options": [
          "Draupadi ka Danda",
          "Nanda Ghunti",
          "Banderpunch",
          "Chaukhamba"
        ],
        "answer": "Chaukhamba"
      },
      {
        "id": 92,
        "question": "Which district of Uttarakhand does not share an international border?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 93,
        "question": "The Lesser Himalayas are separated from 'Doon' by which of the following?",
        "options": [
          "Main Boundary Thrust",
          "Great Boundary Fault",
          "Main Central Thrust",
          "Askot-Baijnath Crystalline Thrust"
        ],
        "answer": "Main Boundary Thrust"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Rivers and Lakes",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "The Bhagirathi River originates from:",
        "options": ["Gomukh", "Gangotri", "Tapovan", "Vishnu Prayag"],
        "answer": "Gomukh"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following rivers does not originate from a glacier?",
        "options": ["Yamuna", "Alaknanda", "Kosi", "Mandakini"],
        "answer": "Kosi"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "The Mandakini River is associated with which water flow (main river)?",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Bhagirathi", "Yamuna", "Dhauliganga"],
        "answer": "Alaknanda"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Which river flows from Kedarnath to Rudra Prayag?",
        "options": ["Bhagirathi", "Alaknanda", "Saryu", "Mandakini"],
        "answer": "Mandakini"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Hemkund Lake is surrounded by:",
        "options": [
          "5 snow-covered peaks",
          "7 snow-covered peaks",
          "8 snow-covered peaks",
          "9 snow-covered peaks"
        ],
        "answer": "7 snow-covered peaks"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following lakes in Uttarakhand is triangular?",
        "options": [
          "Kedarnath Tal",
          "Nainital",
          "Naukuchiatal",
          "Satopanth Lake"
        ],
        "answer": "Kedarnath Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following lakes in Uttarakhand has 9 corners?",
        "options": ["Naukuchiatal", "Bhimtal", "Girital", "Jhilmil Tal"],
        "answer": "Naukuchiatal"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The Kosi River of Uttarakhand is a tributary of:",
        "options": ["Ganga", "Ramganga", "Sharda", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Ramganga"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "The Tehri Dam is located at the confluence of which rivers?",
        "options": [
          "Alaknanda and Mandakini",
          "Bhagirathi and Bhilangana",
          "Bhagirathi and Alaknanda",
          "Kali and Tons"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi and Bhilangana"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "'Jahnavi' River is related to which main river?",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Bhagirathi", "Yamuna", "Eastern Ramganga"],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "For how many years did the 'Gauna Lake' formed by the obstruction of the Birahi Ganga remain?",
        "options": ["84 years", "62 years", "49 years", "77 years"],
        "answer": "62 years"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "The Tehri Dam is located on which river?",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Bhagirathi", "Yamuna", "Mandakini"],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "The confluence of Saryu and Gomti rivers is located at:",
        "options": ["Bageshwar", "Bodihat", "Munisyari", "Tanakpur"],
        "answer": "Bageshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Match the following correctly:\n\nA) Arwa Tal - 1. Uttarkashi\nB) Devi Kund - 2. Pithoragarh\nC) Nanda Kund - 3. Bageshwar\nD) Pari Tal - 4. Chamoli",
        "options": ["A1 B2 C3 D4", "A4 B1 C3 D2", "A4 B3 C1 D2", "A4 B2 C3 D1"],
        "answer": "A4 B1 C3 D2"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Which is the most sacred river of the Kumaon region?",
        "options": ["Kali (Sharda)", "Gomti", "East Dhauliganga", "Saryu"],
        "answer": "Saryu"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "From which place is the Bhagirathi River known as the Ganga?",
        "options": [
          "Vishnu Prayag",
          "Dev Prayag",
          "Karna Prayag",
          "Rudra Prayag"
        ],
        "answer": "Dev Prayag"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Which district has the highest number of natural lakes?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Rudraprayag", "Chamoli", "Bageshwar"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Which lake is known as the 'Mystery Lake' of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Sat Tal", "Roopkund", "Naukuchiatal"],
        "answer": "Roopkund"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Which glacier is fed by the Rakta Varna, Chet Varna, Neelambar, Peetapani, and Chaturangi glaciers?",
        "options": ["Bhagirathi Kharak", "Gangotri", "Satopanth", "Milam"],
        "answer": "Milam"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Which is the largest and deepest lake in the Garhwal region?",
        "options": ["Satopanth Tal", "Sahastra Tal", "Hemkund", "Vishnu Tal"],
        "answer": "Sahastra Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Which is the largest lake in the Kumaon region?",
        "options": ["Bhimtal", "Nainital", "Naukuchiatal", "Sat Tal"],
        "answer": "Bhimtal"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Which of the following passes in Uttarakhand is located near the origin of the Kali River?",
        "options": ["Neeti", "Mana", "Lipulekh", "Milam"],
        "answer": "Lipulekh"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Which is the largest glacier in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Milam", "Kaphini", "Gangotri", "Sundardhunga"],
        "answer": "Gangotri"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "The melting rate of glaciers in the Himalayas is:",
        "options": [
          "Least",
          "Most",
          "Same as glaciers in other parts of the world",
          "No information is available on the melting of Himalayan glaciers"
        ],
        "answer": "Most"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Which Sikh Guru meditated on the banks of Hemkund Lokpal Lake?",
        "options": [
          "Guru Ramdas",
          "Guru Arjan Dev",
          "Guru Har Rai",
          "Guru Govind Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "Guru Govind Singh"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "The Mandakini River originates from which glacier?",
        "options": ["Milam", "Khatling", "Banderpunch", "Chorabari"],
        "answer": "Chorabari"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Which of the following places does not have a hot water spring?",
        "options": ["Badrinath", "Yamunotri", "Gaurikund", "Gangotri"],
        "answer": "Gangotri"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Bhagirathi - Gomukh",
          "East Ramganga - Kalagarh",
          "Bhilangana - Khatling Glacier",
          "Mandakini - Chorabari Tal"
        ],
        "answer": "East Ramganga - Kalagarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Hardy Falls is located in which district?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Uttarkashi", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Which is the largest glacier in the Kumaon region?",
        "options": ["Pindari", "Sundardhunga", "Milam", "Khatling"],
        "answer": "Milam"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "The six-cornered Dodital is located in which district?",
        "options": ["Rudraprayag", "Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "The deepest lake in the Kumaon region, Naukuchiatal, is located in which district?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Pauri", "Bageshwar", "Nainital"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "The origin of the Alaknanda River is:",
        "options": [
          "Milam Glacier",
          "Poting Glacier",
          "Satopanth Glacier",
          "Banderpunch Glacier"
        ],
        "answer": "Satopanth Glacier"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a tributary of the Yamuna River?",
        "options": ["Tons", "Neeti", "Amunag", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Neeti"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Which lake has a horseshoe shape?",
        "options": ["Girital", "Khurpatal", "Sat Tal", "Bhimtal"],
        "answer": "Bhimtal"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Which river is not a tributary of the Saryu River?",
        "options": ["Gomti", "Panar", "East Ramganga", "Ladhiya"],
        "answer": "East Ramganga"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "The city of Bageshwar is situated at the confluence of which rivers?",
        "options": [
          "Pindar and Alaknanda",
          "Kosi and Ramganga",
          "Kali and Gauri",
          "Saryu and Gomti"
        ],
        "answer": "Saryu and Gomti"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "The Baijnath Dham is situated on the banks of which river?",
        "options": ["Gomti", "Kali", "Saryu", "East Ramganga"],
        "answer": "Gomti"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "The valley of which river is called 'Rice Granary' in the Kumaon region?",
        "options": ["Kosi", "Nayar", "Dabka", "Gola"],
        "answer": "Kosi"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Which of the following cold water ponds is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Dev Kund - Uttarkashi",
          "Devi Kund - Bageshwar",
          "Nandi Kund - Rudraprayag",
          "Nanda Kund - Tehri"
        ],
        "answer": "Nanda Kund - Tehri"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Which of the following Kunds (ponds) is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Suraj Kund - Uttarkashi",
          "Tapt Kund - Badrinath",
          "Ret Kund - Champawat",
          "Bhav Kund - Kedarnath"
        ],
        "answer": "Ret Kund - Champawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Where were Mahatma Gandhi's ashes immersed?",
        "options": ["Beni Tal", "Hemkund", "Roopkund", "Vishnu Tal"],
        "answer": "Beni Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Which lake is known as 'Kankali Tal'?",
        "options": ["Hemkund", "Homkund", "Roopkund", "Sahastra Tal"],
        "answer": "Roopkund"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Which Kund (pond) is not located in Chamoli district?",
        "options": ["Basuki Kund", "Hemkund", "Homkund", "Parvati Kund"],
        "answer": "Parvati Kund"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "The Koteshwar Dam is being built on which river?",
        "options": ["Bhagirathi", "Dhauliganga", "Alaknanda", "Birahi Ganga"],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Which Prayag (confluence) is the meeting point of Saraswati and Alaknanda?",
        "options": [
          "Ganesh Prayag",
          "Sone Prayag",
          "Keshav Prayag",
          "Hari Prayag"
        ],
        "answer": "Keshav Prayag"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Which river meets Alaknanda at Rudraprayag?",
        "options": ["Dhauliganga", "Pindar", "Mandakini", "Birahi Ganga"],
        "answer": "Mandakini"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Eastern Dhauliganga is a tributary of which river?",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Kali", "Gomti", "Sharda"],
        "answer": "Kali"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Where is Khatling Glacier located?",
        "options": [
          "Tehri district",
          "Uttarkashi district",
          "Chamoli district",
          "Pithoragarh district"
        ],
        "answer": "Tehri district"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is incorrect?",
        "options": [
          "Dodital - Uttarkashi",
          "Deoria Tal - Tehri",
          "Beni Tal - Chamoli",
          "Basuki Tal - Rudraprayag"
        ],
        "answer": "Deoria Tal - Tehri"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "The Pancheshwar Dam is proposed on which river?",
        "options": ["Ganga", "Yamuna", "Kali", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Kali"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "Which is the longest river in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Kali", "Bhagirathi", "Ramganga", "Alaknanda"],
        "answer": "Kali"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "Where do the Kali and Gauri rivers meet?",
        "options": ["Jauljibi", "Ramnagar", "Dev Prayag", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Jauljibi"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "What is 'Chal Khal' in the hills of Uttarakhand related to?",
        "options": [
          "Water conservation",
          "Fire conservation",
          "Forest conservation",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Water conservation"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Which lake is also known as the 'Mystery Lake'?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Sat Tal", "Roopkund", "Hemkund"],
        "answer": "Roopkund"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "The confluence of Alaknanda and which river occurs at Nandprayag?",
        "options": ["Bhagirathi", "Mandakini", "Vishnuganga", "None of these"],
        "answer": "None of these"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "Which lake is also known as 'Brother-Sister Lake'?",
        "options": ["Mahasar Tal", "Yam Tal", "Siddh Tal", "Narsingh Tal"],
        "answer": "Mahasar Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "Where does the Pindar River originate?",
        "options": [
          "Badrinath",
          "Kedarnath",
          "Pindari Glacier",
          "Milam Glacier"
        ],
        "answer": "Pindari Glacier"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Which lake is known as 'Gandhi Sarovar'?",
        "options": [
          "Chorabari Tal",
          "Nachiketa Tal",
          "Aakhri Tal",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Chorabari Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "Which lake is known as the 'Boiling Lake' of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Sat Tal", "Nainital", "Byatal", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Byatal"
      },
      {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "Which is the deepest lake in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Naukuchiatal", "Dron Sagar", "Nainital", "Girital"],
        "answer": "Naukuchiatal"
      },
      {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "Which river is famous for river rafting in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Ganga", "Bhilangana", "Kali", "Yamuna"],
        "answer": "Ganga"
      },
      {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "The confluence of Alaknanda and Mandakini rivers is located at:",
        "options": ["Rudraprayag", "Karnaprayag", "Devprayag", "Vishnuprayag"],
        "answer": "Rudraprayag"
      },
      {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "By what name are the Bhagirathi and Alaknanda rivers known?",
        "options": [
          "Mother-Daughter",
          "Mother-Sister",
          "Sister-Sister",
          "Mother-Daughter-in-law"
        ],
        "answer": "Mother-Daughter-in-law"
      },
      {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "Which of the following river pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Saryu-Panar",
          "Kali-Gauriganga",
          "Vishnuganga-Dhauli (East)",
          "Bhagirathi-Jadganga"
        ],
        "answer": "Vishnuganga-Dhauli (East)"
      },
      {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "In which district is 'Naldamyanti Tal' located?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Almora", "Pauri", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "Choose the correct pair:",
        "options": [
          "Gangotri Glacier - Uttarkashi",
          "Milam Glacier - Pithoragarh",
          "Satopanth - Chamoli",
          "All pairs are correctly matched"
        ],
        "answer": "All pairs are correctly matched"
      },
      {
        "id": 68,
        "question": "Choose the incorrect pair:",
        "options": [
          "Vishnu Prayag - Alaknanda meets Nandakini",
          "Rudra Prayag - Alaknanda meets Mandakini",
          "Karna Prayag - Alaknanda meets Pindar",
          "Dev Prayag - Alaknanda meets Bhagirathi"
        ],
        "answer": "Vishnu Prayag - Alaknanda meets Nandakini"
      },
      {
        "id": 69,
        "question": "Where is the Kaphini Glacier located?",
        "options": ["Champawat", "Bageshwar", "Pithoragarh", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Bageshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 70,
        "question": "When was the Ganga declared the National River?",
        "options": [
          "August 15, 2001",
          "January 26, 2005",
          "November 4, 2008",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "November 4, 2008"
      },
      {
        "id": 71,
        "question": "The confluence of which rivers is at Nandprayag?",
        "options": [
          "Alaknanda and Vishnuganga",
          "Alaknanda and Nandakini",
          "Alaknanda and Pindar",
          "Alaknanda and Mandakini"
        ],
        "answer": "Alaknanda and Nandakini"
      },
      {
        "id": 72,
        "question": "Which is the largest glacier in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Dunagiri", "Doriari", "Gangotri", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Gangotri"
      },
      {
        "id": 73,
        "question": "The Balganga is a tributary of which river?",
        "options": ["Bhagirathi", "Bhilangana", "Mandakini", "Pindar"],
        "answer": "Bhilangana"
      },
      {
        "id": 74,
        "question": "Which city is located on the 'Gola River'?",
        "options": ["Kashipur", "Champawat", "Haridwar", "Haldwani"],
        "answer": "Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 75,
        "question": "Where is Shyamala Tal located?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Uttarkashi", "Champawat", "Tehri Garhwal"],
        "answer": "Champawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 76,
        "question": "Ladhiya is a tributary of which river?",
        "options": ["Yamuna", "Kali", "Ganga", "Alaknanda"],
        "answer": "Kali"
      },
      {
        "id": 77,
        "question": "What is the origin of the Sharda (Kali) River?",
        "options": ["Pindari", "Kaphini", "Milam", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Milam"
      },
      {
        "id": 78,
        "question": "In which district is the Sundardhunga Glacier located?",
        "options": ["Bageshwar", "Tehri Garhwal", "Uttarkashi", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Bageshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 79,
        "question": "The Jahnavi River is associated with which main river?",
        "options": ["Kali", "Ramganga", "Alaknanda", "Bhagirathi"],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi"
      },
      {
        "id": 80,
        "question": "The Khatling Glacier is the origin of which river?",
        "options": [
          "Jalkur River",
          "Bhilangana River",
          "Pilang Ganga River",
          "Balganga River"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhilangana River"
      },
      {
        "id": 81,
        "question": "In which district of Uttarakhand is Jhilmil Tal located?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Dehradun", "Nainital", "Pithoragarh"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 82,
        "question": "The Eastern Ramganga River originates from:",
        "options": [
          "Pindari Glacier",
          "Nanda Ghunti",
          "Khatling Glacier",
          "Namik Glacier"
        ],
        "answer": "Namik Glacier"
      },
      {
        "id": 83,
        "question": "Where is Satya Kund located?",
        "options": [
          "Dehradun district",
          "Tehri Garhwal district",
          "Uttarkashi district",
          "Chamoli district"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi district"
      },
      {
        "id": 84,
        "question": "What is the origin of the Bhagirathi River?",
        "options": [
          "Mahanadi River",
          "Mandakini River",
          "Yamuna River",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "None of the above"
      },
      {
        "id": 85,
        "question": "In which lake were human skeletons found?",
        "options": ["Hemkund", "Roopkund", "Dodital", "Naukuchiatal"],
        "answer": "Roopkund"
      },
      {
        "id": 86,
        "question": "Which is the largest drainage system in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Yamuna drainage system",
          "Ganga drainage system",
          "Alaknanda drainage system",
          "Kosi drainage system"
        ],
        "answer": "Ganga drainage system"
      },
      {
        "id": 87,
        "question": "Where does the Western Nayar River originate?",
        "options": [
          "Khatling Glacier",
          "Chorabari Tal",
          "Sundardhunga",
          "Dudhatoli range"
        ],
        "answer": "Dudhatoli range"
      },
      {
        "id": 88,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a left bank tributary of the Alaknanda River?",
        "options": ["Mandakini", "Dhauliganga", "Birahi Ganga", "Pindari"],
        "answer": "Pindari"
      },
      {
        "id": 89,
        "question": "Which of the following are tributaries of the Kali River?",
        "options": [
          "Pindari and Dhauliganga",
          "Eastern Dhauli and Kuyi-Yangti",
          "Sang and Kho",
          "Dabka and Nihal"
        ],
        "answer": "Eastern Dhauli and Kuyi-Yangti"
      },
      {
        "id": 90,
        "question": "Which of the following lakes is not located in Chamoli district?",
        "options": [
          "Chakni Tal",
          "Ling Tal (Liga Tal)",
          "Tarak Tal",
          "Gohna Tal"
        ],
        "answer": "Chakni Tal"
      },
      {
        "id": 91,
        "question": "The Tons River is a tributary of which river?",
        "options": ["Dhauliganga", "Pindari", "Yamuna", "Mandakini"],
        "answer": "Yamuna"
      },
      {
        "id": 92,
        "question": "Which of the following rivers is not a tributary of the Ramganga?",
        "options": ["Lisara", "Gangan", "Kosi", "Khod"],
        "answer": "Lisara"
      },
      {
        "id": 93,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a natural lake?",
        "options": ["Tehri Lake", "Khurpa Tal", "Vasuki Lake", "Nachiketa Tal"],
        "answer": "Tehri Lake"
      },
      {
        "id": 94,
        "question": "In which district of Uttarakhand is the Sona Pani Glacier located?",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Chamoli", "Uttarkashi", "Bageshwar"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 95,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Gangotri - Origin of Ganga",
          "Satopanth - Near Badrinath",
          "Milam - North of Gangotri in Mana Valley",
          "Bhagirathi Kharak - Near Badrinath"
        ],
        "answer": "Milam - North of Gangotri in Mana Valley"
      },
      {
        "id": 96,
        "question": "Choose the correctly matched pair:",
        "options": [
          "Dodital - Pauri Garhwal",
          "Nachiketa Tal - Chamoli",
          "Naukuchiatal - Nainital",
          "Deoria Tal - Champawat"
        ],
        "answer": "Naukuchiatal - Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 97,
        "question": "Read the following statements:",
        "options": [
          "Statement 1: Kali is the longest river in Kumaon.",
          "Statement 2: Jauljibi is located at the confluence of the Kali and Gauri rivers.",
          "Which of the above statements is/are correct?",
          "Only 1",
          "Only 2",
          "Both 1 and 2",
          "Both 1 and 2 are incorrect"
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Tradition of Valor, Sports, Awards, Etc.",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Which player is not a resident of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Ekta Bisht",
          "Vandana Kataria",
          "Madhumita Bisht",
          "Jhulan Goswami"
        ],
        "answer": "Jhulan Goswami"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "What was the real name of Chandra Singh Garhwali? (PCS Pre. 2009)",
        "options": [
          "Chandra Singh Negi",
          "Chandra Singh Bhandari",
          "Chandra Singh Kandari",
          "Chandra Singh Bisht"
        ],
        "answer": "Chandra Singh Bhandari"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Who is the first Indian woman to climb Mount Everest? (PCS Main - 2009)",
        "options": [
          "Santosh Yadav",
          "Dicky Dolma",
          "Bachendri Pal",
          "P.T. Usha"
        ],
        "answer": "Bachendri Pal"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "When was the Kumaon Regiment formed? (PCS Main - 2010)",
        "options": ["1944", "1946", "1948", "1945"],
        "answer": "1945"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Since 1887, the headquarters of the Garhwal Regiment has been in:",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Lansdowne", "Landour", "Chakrata"],
        "answer": "Lansdowne"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Who is known as 'Garv Bhanjak' (Pride Breaker)?",
        "options": [
          "Madho Singh Bhandari",
          "Veer Chandra Singh Garhwali",
          "Major Shaitan Singh",
          "Gabar Singh Negi"
        ],
        "answer": "Madho Singh Bhandari"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Who among the following received the Param Vir Chakra?",
        "options": [
          "Major Somnath Sharma",
          "Major Shaitan Singh",
          "Both",
          "Neither"
        ],
        "answer": "Both"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The Auli Winter Sports and Ropeway (Auli Project) was started in:",
        "options": ["1981", "1984", "1982", "1983"],
        "answer": "1983"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Where is Ransi Stadium located?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Pauri", "Nainital", "Kashipur"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Who was the first Victoria Cross winner soldier?",
        "options": [
          "Gabar Singh Negi",
          "Darban Singh Negi",
          "Chandra Singh Garhwali",
          "Madho Singh Bhandari"
        ],
        "answer": "Darban Singh Negi"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Who is the only Test cricket player from Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Sunil Joshi",
          "Mahendra Singh Dhoni",
          "Raghuram Bhatt",
          "Amit Bhandari"
        ],
        "answer": "Mahendra Singh Dhoni"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Which of the following weightlifters was a member of parliament?",
        "options": [
          "Hansa Manral",
          "K.C. Singh 'Baba'",
          "Faiyaz Ahmed",
          "Jagjit Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "K.C. Singh 'Baba'"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Madhumita Bisht is associated with which sport?",
        "options": ["Table Tennis", "Badminton", "Handball", "Lawn Tennis"],
        "answer": "Badminton"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Arjun Award winner Harshwanti Bisht is associated with:",
        "options": ["Mountaineering", "Skiing", "Canoeing", "River Rafting"],
        "answer": "Mountaineering"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "When did Bachendri Pal conquer Mount Everest?",
        "options": [
          "May 24, 1981",
          "May 24, 1983",
          "May 24, 1984",
          "May 24, 1985"
        ],
        "answer": "May 24, 1984"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Who is the only Bharat Ratna recipient from the state? (UDA 2009)",
        "options": [
          "Bhimsen Joshi",
          "H.S. Bahuguna",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Gen. B.C. Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Ballabh Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Who is the first poet from the state to receive the Jnanpith Award?",
        "options": [
          "Sumitra Nandan Pant",
          "Ballabh Dobhal",
          "Shailesh Matiyani",
          "Ganga Prasad Vimal"
        ],
        "answer": "Sumitra Nandan Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Sumitra Nandan Pant was awarded the Jnanpith Award in:",
        "options": ["1965", "1955", "1967", "1968"],
        "answer": "1968"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Major Somnath Sharma, who was posthumously awarded the Param Vir Chakra in 1947, was associated with:",
        "options": [
          "Gorkha Rifles",
          "Garhwal Rifles",
          "Dogra Regiment",
          "Kumaon Regiment"
        ],
        "answer": "Kumaon Regiment"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Who among the following is/are related to the 'Ramon Magsaysay Award'?",
        "options": [
          "Chandi Prasad Bhatt",
          "Deep Joshi",
          "Anil Raturi",
          "Both and (b)"
        ],
        "answer": "Both and (b)"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Choose the correct pair:",
        "options": [
          "Shaitan Singh - Param Vir Chakra",
          "Bhawani Dutt Joshi - Ashok Chakra",
          "Kalu Mehra - Freedom Fighter",
          "All pairs are correct"
        ],
        "answer": "All pairs are correct"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Choose the incorrect pair:",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Harshwanti Bisht - Padma Bhushan",
          "Shukdev Pandey - Padma Shri",
          "Parimarjan Negi - Arjun Award",
          "Deep Joshi - Ramon Magsaysay Award"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Harshwanti Bisht - Padma Bhushan"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "What was the name of the first Param Vir Chakra winner from Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Major Somnath Sharma",
          "Major Gabar Singh",
          "Major Shaitan Singh",
          "Major Saurabh Kalia"
        ],
        "answer": "Major Somnath Sharma"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Gabar Singh Negi is associated with:",
        "options": [
          "Param Vir Chakra",
          "Victoria Cross",
          "Mahavir Chakra",
          "Ashok Chakra"
        ],
        "answer": "Victoria Cross"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Who was the first from Uttarakhand to receive the Dronacharya Award?",
        "options": [
          "Hari Singh Thapa",
          "Unmukt Chand",
          "Manish Pandey",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "None of these"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Who was the first from Uttarakhand to receive the Rajiv Gandhi Khel Ratna Award?",
        "options": [
          "Mohammad Ranjan Negi",
          "Jaspal Rana",
          "Abhinav Sindhu",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Jaspal Rana"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "When was the military cantonment established in Chakrata?",
        "options": ["1857 AD", "1862 AD", "1869 AD", "None of these"],
        "answer": "1869 AD"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Who was awarded the 'National Adventure Award' in 1994?",
        "options": [
          "Suman Kutiyal",
          "Harshwanti Bisht",
          "Chandraprabha Aitwal",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Chandraprabha Aitwal"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of the 'Garhwal Regiment' located?",
        "options": ["Chakrata", "Ranikhet", "Dehradun", "Lansdowne"],
        "answer": "Lansdowne"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Choose the incorrect pair:",
        "options": [
          "Deep Joshi - Ramon Magsaysay",
          "Sundar Lal Bahuguna - Ramon Magsaysay",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant - Bharat Ratna",
          "Hansa Manral - Dronacharya Award"
        ],
        "answer": "Sundar Lal Bahuguna - Ramon Magsaysay"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "In which year did Chandi Prasad Bhatt receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award?",
        "options": ["1981", "1982", "1984", "1985"],
        "answer": "1982"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Who among the following has not received the Padma Shri award?",
        "options": [
          "Pushpesh Pant",
          "Dr. Shekhar Pathak",
          "Anil Prakash Joshi",
          "K.P. Nautiyal"
        ],
        "answer": "K.P. Nautiyal"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Parimarjan Negi is a famous player of:",
        "options": ["Cricket", "Chess", "Judo", "Hockey"],
        "answer": "Chess"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is incorrect?",
        "options": [
          "Chandraprabha Aitwal - Mountaineer",
          "Unmukt Chand - Cricket",
          "Ekta Bisht - Cricket",
          "Bachendri Pal - Shooting"
        ],
        "answer": "Bachendri Pal - Shooting"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Who among the following advocated for the Garhwali soldiers in the 'Peshawar Kand'?",
        "options": [
          "Mukundi Lal",
          "Anusuya Prasad Jugudan",
          "Tara Dutt Gairola",
          "Mathura Prasad Naithani"
        ],
        "answer": "Mukundi Lal"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Which player from Uttarakhand won a gold medal in the 22nd Commonwealth Games?",
        "options": [
          "Jaspal Rana",
          "Lakshya Sen",
          "Vandana Kataria",
          "Virag Sen"
        ],
        "answer": "Lakshya Sen"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "In October 2022, on which peak did trainees from the Nehru Institute of Mountaineering die due to an avalanche?",
        "options": [
          "Tabchu-1",
          "Chandrabhaga",
          "Draupadi ka Danda-2",
          "Hanuman Tibba"
        ],
        "answer": "Draupadi ka Danda-2"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "When did Bachendri Pal receive the Padma Shri award?",
        "options": ["1982", "1996", "1988", "1984"],
        "answer": "1984"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Which of the following players is not a resident of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Lakshya Sen",
          "Unmukt Chand",
          "Ekta Bisht",
          "Madhumita Goswami"
        ],
        "answer": "Madhumita Goswami"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Match the following:",
        "pairs": [
          "A) Darban Singh Negi - 1. Victoria Cross",
          "B) Govind Ballabh Pant - 2. Bharat Ratna",
          "C) Hansa Manral - 3. Dronacharya Award",
          "D) Deep Joshi - 4. Ramon Magsaysay"
        ],
        "options": ["A4 B3 C2 D1", "A1 B2 C3 D4", "A2 B4 C1 D3", "A3 B4 C2 D1"],
        "answer": "A3 B4 C2 D1"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Science - Technology, Environment, and Ancient Measurement Systems",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Where is the UK Biotechnology Council located?",
        "options": ["Pantnagar", "Haldwani", "Patwadangar", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "How many 'mutthi' are in one kilogram?",
        "options": ["16 mutthi", "20 mutthi", "32 mutthi", "8 mutthi"],
        "answer": "16 mutthi"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Where is the largest biodiversity park located?",
        "options": ["Pantnagar", "Dehradun", "Haldwani", "Srinagar"],
        "answer": "Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "The Hermitage building has been established to provide the latest IT technologies in one place in:",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Haridwar", "Dehradun", "Jolly Grant"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "An IT park has been established in an area of 65 acres in:",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Pantnagar", "Haldwani", "Kotdwar"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "The Biotechnology Institute has been established in:",
        "options": ["Patwadangar", "Pantnagar", "Roorkee", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Patwadangar"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "When was the e-District scheme launched in the state?",
        "options": ["2001", "2005", "2009", "2010"],
        "answer": "2009"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The Ganga River was declared a 'National River' on:",
        "options": [
          "November 8, 2008",
          "November 4, 2008",
          "December 10, 2009",
          "December 25, 2014"
        ],
        "answer": "November 4, 2008"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is related to remote sensing?",
        "options": ["UCOST", "USAC", "UCB", "USERC"],
        "answer": "USAC"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Where has Vigyan Dham been established?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Srinagar", "Rishikesh"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "One 'naali' of land is equal to:",
        "options": [
          "100 square meters",
          "200 square meters",
          "500 square meters",
          "1000 square meters"
        ],
        "answer": "200 square meters"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "UCB - Haldwani",
          "USERC - Dehradun",
          "USAC - Dehradun",
          "UCOST - Mussoorie"
        ],
        "answer": "UCOST - Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "IT Academy - Narendra Nagar",
          "IT Park - Srinagar",
          "Biotechnology Council - Haldwani, Pantnagar",
          "Software Technology Park - Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "IT Park - Srinagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "In Uttarakhand, the 'Sparsh Ganga Abhiyan' was launched in:",
        "options": ["2006", "2009", "2011", "2013"],
        "answer": "2009"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Which city is being developed as a Solar City by the central government?",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Nainital", "Dehradun", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Where is the IT Park located in Uttarakhand? (Assistant Engineer)",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Dehradun", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Pauri"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Where is India's first Liquid Mirror Telescope located? (Patwari/Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": ["Ramgarh", "Hartola", "Devasthal", "Patwadangar"],
        "answer": "Devasthal"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Where has the Indian Meteorological Department established a 'Doppler Weather Radar' in Uttarakhand? (PCS - 2023)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Chakrata", "Mukteshwar", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Mukteshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Where is Vigyan Dham located in Uttarakhand? (Forest Guard - 2023)",
        "options": ["Pauri", "Karnaprayag", "Dehradun", "Mussoorie"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Which state hosted India's first Rural Science Congress held in February 2023? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["Andhra Pradesh", "Kerala", "Maharashtra", "Uttarakhand"],
        "answer": "Uttarakhand"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Who among the following has been appointed as the Director General of the Uttarakhand State Council for Science and Technology (UCOST) by the Uttarakhand government? (Forest Guard - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Rajendra Dobhal",
          "Dr. Anil Prakash Joshi",
          "Prof. Durgesh Pant",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Prof. Durgesh Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "How many 'mutthi' are in one 'naali' of land in Uttarakhand? (Forest Guard - 2023)",
        "options": ["15", "16", "17", "18"],
        "answer": "16"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "In which district of Uttarakhand was the e-District project first launched as a pilot project? (Patwari/Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": ["Pauri", "Rudraprayag", "Nainital", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Prominent Personalities",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Garhwal Paintings'? (PCS Main: 2006)",
        "options": ["Mukundi Lal", "H.G. Walton", "Molaram", "Patiram"],
        "answer": "Mukundi Lal"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Who is considered the first freedom fighter of Kumaon? (PCS Main: 2006)",
        "options": [
          "Kalu Mehra",
          "Mohan Singh Mehta",
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant"
        ],
        "answer": "Kalu Mehra"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Which freedom fighter is known as 'Garh Kesari'? (PCS Main: 2003, 2009 & Group: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Gumani Pant",
          "Indramani Badoni",
          "Anusuya Prasad Bahuguna",
          "Badridutt Pandey"
        ],
        "answer": "Badridutt Pandey"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Sumitranandan Pant is famous as a (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": [
          "Devotional poet",
          "Progressive poet",
          "Chhayavadi poet",
          "Heroic poet"
        ],
        "answer": "Chhayavadi poet"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": [
          "Bachendri Pal - Mountaineering",
          "Bindeshwari Pathak - Social Worker",
          "Giriraj Kishore - Litterateur",
          "Sunder Lal Bahuguna - Musician"
        ],
        "answer": "Sunder Lal Bahuguna - Musician"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Who is famous as 'Vriksh Manav' (Tree Man)? (PCS Main: 2003 & Group G: 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Chandi Prasad Bhatt",
          "Sunder Lal Bahuguna",
          "Vishveshwar Dutt Saklani"
        ],
        "answer": "Vishveshwar Dutt Saklani"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Who among the following is a renowned painter?",
        "options": [
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Sudhir Ranjan Khastgir",
          "Shailesh Matiyani",
          "Sunder Lal Bahuguna"
        ],
        "answer": "Sudhir Ranjan Khastgir"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Which leader died in jail in 1942 due to a hunger strike? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": [
          "Daulat Ram",
          "Narendra Dutt Saklani",
          "Dev Suman",
          "Manvendra Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "Dev Suman"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Who is known by the name 'Dharan'? (PCS Main: 2003 & Group G: 2016, RO/ARO: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Hari Krishna Raturi",
          "Mukundi Lal",
          "Shiv Prasad Dabral"
        ],
        "answer": "Shiv Prasad Dabral"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Who is known as 'Kumaon Kesari'? (PCS Main: 2003, 2009 & Group G: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Hargovind Pant",
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Indra Singh Nayal"
        ],
        "answer": "Badridutt Pandey"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Badridutt Pandey was:",
        "options": [
          "Leader of the Coolie-Begar Movement",
          "Member of the Indian National Congress",
          "Member of the Hindu Mahasabha",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Leader of the Coolie-Begar Movement"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Who is the author of 'Borivali to Boribandar'? (PCS Main: 2004)",
        "options": [
          "Ramesh Chandra Shah",
          "Gaura Pant 'Shivani'",
          "Mrinal Pande",
          "Shailesh Matiyani"
        ],
        "answer": "Shailesh Matiyani"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Who among the following was given the title 'Pandit'? (EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Nain Singh Rawat",
          "Gabar Singh",
          "Madho Singh Bhandari",
          "Darban Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "Nain Singh Rawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Who is the only person from the state to receive the Jnanpith Award for literature? (UDA: 2009)",
        "options": [
          "Liladhar Jagudi",
          "Viren Dangwal",
          "Sumitranandan Pant",
          "Ila Chandra Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Sumitranandan Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Who is the only person from Uttarakhand to receive the 'Bharat Ratna'? (UDA: 2009)",
        "options": [
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Gen. B.C. Joshi",
          "Bhimsen Joshi",
          "H.N. Bahuguna"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Ballabh Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Who is the first woman from Uttarakhand to go to jail during the freedom movement?",
        "options": [
          "Sarla Behen",
          "Kunti Verma",
          "Bishni Devi Shah",
          "Vidyavati Dobhal"
        ],
        "answer": "Bishni Devi Shah"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Who is called the 'Lakshmibai of Kumaon'?",
        "options": [
          "Karnavati",
          "Jiya Rani",
          "Kamalendu Mati Shah",
          "Bishni Devi Shah"
        ],
        "answer": "Jiya Rani"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Who is the author of the Garhwali play 'Bindra'? (Forest Guard: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Haridutt Bhatt 'Shailesh'",
          "Dr. Purushottam Dobhal",
          "Manglesh Dabral",
          "Bhagwati Prasad Chandola"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Purushottam Dobhal"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Ranveer Singh Bisht is associated with (PCS: 2010)",
        "options": ["Painting", "Literature", "Military", "Science"],
        "answer": "Painting"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Who is the first woman Major General not only in India but in the world?",
        "options": [
          "Prabha Kiran",
          "Bhawna Gurunani",
          "Kumari Maya Tamta",
          "Diksha Bisht"
        ],
        "answer": "Kumari Maya Tamta"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Who is the woman honored with the Dronacharya Award?",
        "options": [
          "Shalini Shah",
          "Hansa Manral",
          "Pratibha Upadhyay",
          "Niharika Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "Hansa Manral"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Who is the first 'Mouth and Foot Painting Artist' of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Ramesh Bisht",
          "Anand Singh Bisht",
          "Hari Ram Kohli",
          "Ganga Singh Rana"
        ],
        "answer": "Hari Ram Kohli"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Who said, 'If we have to die, it is better to die proclaiming our principles and beliefs publicly'?",
        "options": [
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Shridev Suman",
          "Indramani Badoni",
          "Bhawani Singh Rawat"
        ],
        "answer": "Shridev Suman"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Who is credited with starting the Gandhian movement in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Prayag Dutt Pant",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Hargovind Pant"
        ],
        "answer": "Prayag Dutt Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Who is known as the 'Advertising Guru'?",
        "options": [
          "Shekhar Joshi",
          "Prasoon Joshi",
          "Ruskin Bond",
          "Shekhar Pathak"
        ],
        "answer": "Prasoon Joshi"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched? (Lecturer: 09)",
        "options": [
          "Khandimsar Bhatt - Environment",
          "Bachendri Pal - Mountaineering",
          "Jaspal Rana - Literature",
          "B.C. Khanduri - Politics"
        ],
        "answer": "Jaspal Rana - Literature"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Who established 'Shanti Kunj' in Haridwar? (Lecturer: 09)",
        "options": [
          "Swami Ramtirth",
          "Swami Sahajanand",
          "Pt. Shri Ram Sharma",
          "Vivekananda"
        ],
        "answer": "Pt. Shri Ram Sharma"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Who led the Chipko Movement? (Lecturer: 09)",
        "options": ["Gaura Devi", "Sarla Devi", "Radha Bhatt", "Teelu Rauteli"],
        "answer": "Gaura Devi"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Which of the following names and surnames is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Lok Ratna Pant - Gumani",
          "Sumitranandan Pant - Saundarya Kavi",
          "Nain Singh Rawat - Maulik Pandit",
          "Girish Tiwari - Gorada"
        ],
        "answer": "Girish Tiwari - Gorada"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Who was known as 'Gosai Dutt' in childhood? (RO/ARO: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Lok Ratna Pant",
          "Sumitranandan Pant",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Gangadutt Upreti"
        ],
        "answer": "Sumitranandan Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "The 'Dola-Palki' movement was related to which community? (EO/RL: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Other Backward Class",
          "Kshatriya Caste",
          "Scheduled Tribe",
          "Dalit"
        ],
        "answer": "Dalit"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Who was the first elected Member of Parliament from the Garhwal Lok Sabha constituency? (RO/ARO: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Bhakt Darshan",
          "Kamalendu Mati Shah",
          "D.D. Pant",
          "Mukundi Lal"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhakt Darshan"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Which of the following names and their fields of work is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Nilambar Pant - Space Science",
          "Khadag Singh Valdiya - Geology",
          "Aditya Narayan Purohit - Agricultural Science",
          "Devidan Pant - Medical Science"
        ],
        "answer": "Devidan Pant - Medical Science"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Which of the following names and their fields of work is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Uttam Das - Music",
          "Avdhesh Kaushal - Environment",
          "Vidyavati Dobhal - Film",
          "Narayan Singh Thapa - Cinematography"
        ],
        "answer": "Vidyavati Dobhal - Film"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Who among the following is known as the expert of the 'Bol Sagar'?",
        "options": [
          "Uttam Das",
          "Keshavdas Anuragi",
          "Yashodhar Mathpal",
          "Chandra Singh Rahi"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttam Das"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Where was the Garhwal Seva Sangh established in 1936? (RO/ARO: 2023)",
        "options": ["Allahabad", "Delhi", "Dehradun", "Lucknow"],
        "answer": "Delhi"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Who established the 'Himalayan Institute Hospital Trust' in Jolly Grant in 1989?",
        "options": [
          "Swami Matmanan",
          "Swami Ram",
          "Swami Shivanand",
          "Acharya Shri Ram Sharma"
        ],
        "answer": "Swami Ram"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "The Chipko Movement started as a reaction to which of the following? (EO/RL: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Shell Sports Goods Factory",
          "Simon Sports Goods Factory",
          "Springer Sports Goods Factory",
          "Southampton Sports Goods Factory"
        ],
        "answer": "Simon Sports Goods Factory"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Who laid the foundation of the Vivekananda Parvatiya Krishi Anusandhan Sansthan in Almora in 1924? (RO/ARO: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Nain Singh",
          "Boshi Sen",
          "Nilambar Joshi",
          "Dr. Khajan Chand"
        ],
        "answer": "Boshi Sen"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Whose famous work is 'Aryon ka Adi Niwas - Madhya Himalaya'?",
        "options": [
          "Bhajan Singh 'Singh'",
          "Dr. Shiv Prasad Dabral",
          "Dr. Pitambar Dutt Badthwal",
          "Mukundram Badthwal"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhajan Singh 'Singh'"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Who wrote the history of Uttarakhand in 12 volumes?",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Shiv Prasad Dabral 'Charan'",
          "Bhajan Singh",
          "Dr. Pitambar Dutt Badthwal",
          "Lalita Prasad Naithani"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Shiv Prasad Dabral 'Charan'"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Which of the following scholars from the state received titles like 'Mahamahopadhyay' and 'Shambarth Maharath'? (Computer Operator: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Shashidhar Sharma",
          "Prof. D.D. Sharma",
          "Acharya Bhaskaranand",
          "Dr. Shiv Prasad Dabral 'Charan'"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Shashidhar Sharma"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Whose famous play is 'Jai Bharat - Jai Uttarakhand'?",
        "options": [
          "Rajendra Dhasmana",
          "Liladhar Jagudi",
          "Shailesh Matiyani",
          "Manohar Shyam Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Rajendra Dhasmana"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Who wrote the book 'Garhwal Ancient and Modern'? (Junior Assistant: 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Hari Krishna Raturi",
          "Chandra Singh Garhwali",
          "William Sax",
          "Patiram"
        ],
        "answer": "Patiram"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "Who wrote the famous poem 'Pahad Ke Aage Bhitar Pahad' after being affected by the Muzaffarnagar incident during the statehood movement?",
        "options": [
          "Balwant Manral",
          "Manohar Shyam Joshi",
          "Virendra Dangwal",
          "Girish Tiwari 'Girda'"
        ],
        "answer": "Balwant Manral"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Who wrote the famous creation 'Uttarakhand Kitna Sach Aur Kitna Chhal'?",
        "options": [
          "Govind Chatak",
          "Manohar Shyam Joshi",
          "Surendra Singh Pangti",
          "Satya Prasad Raturi"
        ],
        "answer": "Surendra Singh Pangti"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Who is the author of the story 'Garhwali Thaat'? (Patwari Lekhpal: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Govind Prasad Ghildiyal",
          "Dayanand Bahuguna",
          "Sadanand Kukreti",
          "Bhairav Dutt Dhuliya"
        ],
        "answer": "Sadanand Kukreti"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Who is famous in the history of Garhwal as 'Naak Katne Wali Rani' (Nose Cutting Queen)? (PCS 2012 & Group G: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Rani Karnavati",
          "Rani Guleria",
          "Rani Nepaliya",
          "Rani Kamlendumati"
        ],
        "answer": "Rani Karnavati"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Who is known as 'Uttarakhand's Gandhi'? (PCS: 2012, Group G: 2016, 2017, Lecturer: 2019)",
        "options": [
          "Indramani Badoni",
          "Sunderlal Bahuguna",
          "Gaura Devi",
          "Madho Singh Bhandari"
        ],
        "answer": "Indramani Badoni"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Who among the following is not a Kumaoni writer? (Village Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Gumani",
          "Gauri Dutt Pandey 'Gorda'",
          "Shivdutt Sati",
          "Liladhar Jagudi"
        ],
        "answer": "Liladhar Jagudi"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "When was Gaura Pant (Shivani) born? (Computer Operator: 2016)",
        "options": ["1913", "1923", "1932", "1823"],
        "answer": "1923"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "Molaram was a famous: (Village Development Officer: 2016)",
        "options": ["Painter", "Historian", "Katyuri ruler", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Painter"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "Choose the correct pair: (Junior Assistant: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Chipko Movement - Women's Safety",
          "Mixed Forest (Mishrit Van) - Anil Kumar Pandey",
          "Maiti Movement - Tree Plantation",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Maiti Movement - Tree Plantation"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "Pushpesh Pant is known in which field? (Jail Guard: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Politician",
          "Scientist",
          "Expert in International Affairs",
          "Mathematician"
        ],
        "answer": "Expert in International Affairs"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Who is the first woman Director General of Police in Uttarakhand? (Female Sub Inspector: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Ashok Kant Sharan",
          "Kanchan Chaudhary Bhattacharya",
          "Kanchan Pant",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Kanchan Chaudhary Bhattacharya"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "Choose the correct pair: (Female Sub Inspector: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Badridutt Pandey's other name - Kumaon Kesari",
          "Indramani Badoni's other name - Uttarakhand's Gandhi",
          "Both and (b)",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Both and (b)"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "By what name is Vishweshwar Dutt Saklani known? (Sugarcane Supervisor: 2016)",
        "options": ["World Manav", "Tree Manav", "State Manav", "North Manav"],
        "answer": "Tree Manav"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "By what other name is 'Irene Pant' known? (Female Constable: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Daughter of Almora",
          "Queen of Kumaon",
          "Daughter-in-law of Pakistan",
          "Both and (c)"
        ],
        "answer": "Both and (c)"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Sumitranandan Pant received the Jnanpith Award for which of his creations? (Village Development Officer: 2016)",
        "options": ["Lokayatana", "Veena", "Chidambara", "Pallava"],
        "answer": "Chidambara"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "Shiv Prasad Dabral is a: (Computer Operator: 2016)",
        "options": ["Politician", "Philosopher", "Historian", "Poet"],
        "answer": "Historian"
      },
      {
        "id": 81,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book titled 'Hari Bhari Ummeed' based on the Chipko Movement?",
        "options": [
          "Dham Singh Negi",
          "Vijay Jadhari",
          "Ramchandra Guha",
          "Shekhar Pathak"
        ],
        "answer": "Shekhar Pathak"
      },
      {
        "id": 82,
        "question": "Which story by Shekhar Joshi was made into a film by the Children's Film Society?",
        "options": ["Kosi Ka Ghatwar", "Galta Loha", "Halkaha", "Chajju"],
        "answer": "Chajju"
      },
      {
        "id": 83,
        "question": "Dr. Pitambar Dutt Barthwal is the first person to receive a D.Litt. degree in Hindi literature. In which language did he present his thesis?",
        "options": ["English", "Hindi", "Kumaoni", "Garhwali"],
        "answer": "English"
      },
      {
        "id": 84,
        "question": "'Gosai Dutt' is the original name of which of the following writers?",
        "options": [
          "Pitambar Dutt Barthwal",
          "Sumitranandan Pant",
          "Manglesh Dabral",
          "Shekhar Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Sumitranandan Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 85,
        "question": "Who was first awarded the Khel Ratna Award from Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Jaspal Rana",
          "Ekta Bisht",
          "Meir Ranjan Negi",
          "Chandraprabha Aitwal"
        ],
        "answer": "Jaspal Rana"
      },
      {
        "id": 86,
        "question": "In which year was the Uttarakhand Gaurav Samman started?",
        "options": ["2020", "2021", "2022", "2019"],
        "answer": "2021"
      },
      {
        "id": 87,
        "question": "Which of the following names was not on the 2022 Uttarakhand Gaurav Samman list?",
        "options": [
          "Biren Dangwal",
          "Ajit Doval",
          "Narendra Singh Negi",
          "Girish Chandra Tiwari"
        ],
        "answer": "Narendra Singh Negi"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand Organizations, Institutions, and Museums",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of the Indian Survey Department located? (PCS Pre: 2007)",
        "options": ["Chandigarh", "Hyderabad", "Dehradun", "New Delhi"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Where is the National Academy of Public Administration located? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Mussoorie", "Haridwar", "Ranikhet"],
        "answer": "Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Where is the Uttarakhand Administrative Training Academy located?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Tehri", "Roorkee"],
        "answer": "Roorkee"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Where was the State Observatory established in 1955?",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Uttarkashi", "Pithoragarh", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "In which year was the State Public Service Commission formed?",
        "options": ["2000", "2001", "2002", "2003"],
        "answer": "2001"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "In which year was the Indian Institute of Forest Research established in Dehradun?",
        "options": ["1906", "1947", "1954", "1975"],
        "answer": "1906"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Where is the National Remote Sensing Institute located?",
        "options": ["New Delhi", "Dehradun", "Lucknow", "Nagpur"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Where was the Indian Institute of Management (IIM) established?",
        "options": ["Haldwani", "Pantnagar", "Kashipur", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Where is the Rajkiya Kendra located?",
        "options": ["Haldwani", "Dehradun", "Kashipur", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Where is the Himalayan Cultural Center located?",
        "options": [
          "Dehradun",
          "Nainital",
          "Bhimtal",
          "Bholaram Museum (Tehri)"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhimtal"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Where is the Indian Remote Sensing Institute located? (PCS Pre: 2012)",
        "options": ["New Delhi", "Dehradun", "Lucknow", "Nagpur"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Where was the IIM established? (Group 'G': 2011)",
        "options": ["Haldwani", "Pantnagar", "Kashipur", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Where is the Rajkiya Kendra located? (Group 'G': 2011)",
        "options": ["Haldwani", "Dehradun", "Kashipur", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Himalayan Cultural Center - Dehradun",
          "Himalayan Museum - Nainital",
          "Folk Culture Museum - Bhimtal",
          "Bholaram Museum - Tehri"
        ],
        "answer": "Bholaram Museum - Tehri"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Where was the Uttarakhand Renewable Energy Development Corporation established?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Pithoragarh", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Where is the National Institute for the Visually Handicapped located?",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Dehradun", "Nainital", "K.S.N."],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Where was the ITBT established?",
        "options": ["Roorkee", "Kashipur", "Haldwani", "Rishikesh"],
        "answer": "Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "In which district of the state was the Hydropower Institute recently established?",
        "options": ["Tehri", "Roorkee", "Kashipur", "Pantnagar"],
        "answer": "Tehri"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Where has the Ministry of Defense established the Defense Agricultural Research Institute?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Lansdowne", "Almora", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Which of the following is not located in Dehradun?",
        "options": [
          "Survey of India",
          "Institute of Drilling Technology",
          "Industrial Toxicological Research Center",
          "Indian Wildlife Institute"
        ],
        "answer": "Industrial Toxicological Research Center"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Where was the Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES) established?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Nainital", "Haridwar", "Roorkee"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Where is the Uttarakhand Judicial and Legal Academy located?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Nainital", "Almora", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Where was the Nehru Institute of Mountaineering established?",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Where was Kumaon's first tuberculosis sanatorium established? (APO: 2011)",
        "options": ["Bhowali"],
        "answer": "Bhowali"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Where is the Police Training Academy located?",
        "options": ["Narendra Nagar"],
        "answer": "Narendra Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Where is the Wildlife Institute of India located? (APO: 2021)",
        "options": ["Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Where is the Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants (CIMAP) established?",
        "options": ["Pantnagar"],
        "answer": "Pantnagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Where is the Tasar Research Center located?",
        "options": ["Majkhali"],
        "answer": "Majkhali"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Where is the State Disaster Mitigation and Management Center located?",
        "options": ["Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Where is the Vivekananda Parvatiya Krishi Anusandhan Sansthan established? (Upper Private Secretary - 2016, EO/RI: 2021)",
        "options": ["Almora"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "Where is the Lal Bahadur Shastri National Academy of Administration located? (PCS Pre: 2014)",
        "options": ["Delhi", "Nainital", "Mussoorie", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Mussoorie"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Who was the first chairman of the Uttarakhand Public Service Commission? (PCS Pre: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Shri A.P. Navani",
          "B.A.K. Das",
          "Lt. Gen. G.S. Negi",
          "Dr. M.C. Sati"
        ],
        "answer": "Shri A.P. Navani"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Where is the Wadia Institute of Himalayan Geology located? (Assistant Accountant - Computer Operator: 2016)",
        "options": ["Delhi", "Dehradun", "Nainital", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Where is the Uday Shankar Dance and Drama Academy located? (Assistant Director - 2016)",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Almora", "Srinagar", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Where is the Indira Gandhi National Forest Academy located? (Jail Guard)",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Bhimtal", "Dehradun", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Where is the Bhuvaneshwari Mahila Ashram located? (Female Sub Inspector: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Anjani Sain (Tehri Garhwal)",
          "Gairsain (Chamoli)",
          "Kot (Bageshwar)",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Anjani Sain (Tehri Garhwal)"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Which of the following institutions are located in Dehradun? (Female Sub Inspector: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Indian Remote Sensing Institute",
          "Indian Military Academy",
          "Defense Electronics Application Laboratory",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "In which district of Uttarakhand is the 'National Institute of Technology' located? (Female Constable: 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Pauri Garhwal",
          "Udham Singh Nagar",
          "Dehradun",
          "Nainital"
        ],
        "answer": "Pauri Garhwal"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Where is the Indian Institute of Management (IIM) located? (Female Constable: 2016)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Kashipur", "Haridwar", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Where is the Folk Culture Museum located? (Patwari: 2016)",
        "options": ["Khutani", "Ranikhet", "Kashipur", "Champawat"],
        "answer": "Khutani"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Where is the 'Wildlife Institute of India' located? (Patwari: 2016)",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Dehradun", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Where is the Herbal Research Institute located in Uttarakhand? (Patwari: 2016)",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Champawat", "Gopeshwar", "Bageshwar"],
        "answer": "Gopeshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Where is the All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) located in Uttarakhand? (Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Rishikesh", "Kotdwar", "Haldwani"],
        "answer": "Rishikesh"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Where is the 'Wildlife Conservation Training Center' located in Uttarakhand? (Social Welfare Officer: 2017)",
        "options": ["Almora", "Kalagarh", "Nainital", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Kalagarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "Where is the Uttarakhand Tea Development Board established? (Social Welfare Officer: 2017)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Bageshwar", "Almora", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Bageshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Where is the butterfly museum established by Frederic Smetacek located? (Seed Inspector: 2017)",
        "options": ["Khurpatal", "Nainital", "Saat Tal", "Bhimtal"],
        "answer": "Bhimtal"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Who is credited with establishing the Kumaon Geology Institute? (UK PCS/RO/ARO: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Khadak Singh Valdia",
          "Dr. Kamal Joshi",
          "Dr. Anil Prakash Joshi",
          "Prof. Robert Koch"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Khadak Singh Valdia"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "When was the Nehru Institute of Mountaineering established? (State Supervisor 2017)",
        "options": ["1947", "1965", "1991", "None of these"],
        "answer": "1965"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "In which year was the headquarters of the Survey of India, established in Bengal, shifted to Dehradun? (Junior Assistant: 2018)",
        "options": ["1940", "1941", "1942", "None of these"],
        "answer": "1942"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "When was the Kumaon Mandal Vikas Nigam established? (Junior Assistant: 2016)",
        "options": ["1976", "1980", "1992", "None of these"],
        "answer": "1976"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "Where is the Irrigation Research Institute located in Uttarakhand? (Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Kashipur", "Dehradun", "Roorkee"],
        "answer": "Roorkee"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "When was the Survey of India, established in Bengal in 1767 AD, shifted to Dehradun? (PRO: 2021)",
        "options": ["1942", "1802", "1788", "1796"],
        "answer": "1942"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "Who is the founder of the 'Himalayan Environmental Studies and Conservation Organization'? (VDO: 2021)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Khadak Singh Valdia",
          "Dr. Kamal Joshi",
          "Dr. Anil Prakash Joshi",
          "Rajiv Nayan Bahuguna"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Anil Prakash Joshi"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "The 'Indian Veterinary Research Institute' in Mukteshwar was established in 1893 by whom? (VDO: 2021)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Alfred Lingard",
          "Victor Mohan Joshi",
          "Dr. C.G. Blanfield",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Alfred Lingard"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Where is the 'Folk Culture Museum' located? (DEO: 2021)",
        "options": ["Kalabungi", "Khutani", "Ranikhet", "Bagnath"],
        "answer": "Khutani"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "When was the Forest Research Institute established? (PCS: 2022, 2023)",
        "options": ["1896", "1906", "1910", "1950"],
        "answer": "1906"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "Where has the Indian Meteorological Department established a Doppler Weather Radar? (PCS: 2022)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Chakrata", "Mukteshwar", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Mukteshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "Which of the following institutions is not located in Uttarakhand? (Forester: 2022)",
        "options": ["CBRI", "ONGC", "HAL", "BHEL"],
        "answer": "HAL"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "In which district is the Govind Ballabh Pant State Museum located? (Steno Assistant: 2021)",
        "options": ["Champawat", "Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "Where is the Uttarakhand Herb Research and Development Institute located? (Forest Guard: 2020)",
        "options": ["Ramnagar", "Gopeshwar", "Bageshwar", "Jageshwar"],
        "answer": "Gopeshwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is correctly matched? (Patwari/Lekhpal: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Wadia Institute of Himalayan Geology - Dehradun",
          "Vivekananda Agricultural Research Institute - Pithoragarh",
          "Indian Military Academy - Haridwar",
          "High Altitude Plant Physiology Research Center - Chamoli"
        ],
        "answer": "Wadia Institute of Himalayan Geology - Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 62,
        "question": "The Himalayan Spice Garden was established by the Forest Research Centre, Haldwani, in: (Patwari/Lekhpal: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Sattal, Nainital",
          "Pathri, Haridwar",
          "Soni, Ranikhet",
          "Vikasnagar, Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "Soni, Ranikhet"
      },
      {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": ["B.D.P.L.", "B.H.E.L.", "B.E.L.", "I.P.R.I."],
        "answer": "I.P.R.I."
      },
      {
        "id": 64,
        "question": "Where was the M.S.M.E. Ministry's M.A.I.T.I. Dool Room established? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Sidcul, Sitarganj",
          "Sidcul, Haridwar",
          "Sidcul, Sevakurd",
          "Sidcul, Bajpur"
        ],
        "answer": "Sidcul, Sitarganj"
      },
      {
        "id": 65,
        "question": "Who founded the 'Happy Club' organization? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Malti Devi",
          "Tika Singh",
          "Hargovind Pant",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Ballabh Pant"
      },
      {
        "id": 66,
        "question": "Who is credited with the establishment of the Garhwal Regimental Centre? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Darwan Singh Negi",
          "Jaswant Singh Negi",
          "Kunwar Singh Rawat",
          "Balabhadra Singh Negi"
        ],
        "answer": "Darwan Singh Negi"
      },
      {
        "id": 67,
        "question": "In which year was the 'Parvatiya Rajya Parishad' established? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "June 25, 1967",
          "June 25, 1968",
          "June 25, 1969",
          "June 25, 1970"
        ],
        "answer": "June 25, 1967"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Education, Language, Literature, Books",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "In which district is Kanvashram located? (Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2016)",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Uttarkashi", "Pauri", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Which is the main method of worshiping Shiva? (PCS Pre: 2007)",
        "options": ["Madhya Pradesh", "Uttarakhand", "Haryana", "Assam"],
        "answer": "Uttarakhand"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "In which year did Roorkee Engineering University acquire university status? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": ["5th IIT", "6th IIT", "7th IIT", "8th IIT"],
        "answer": "7th IIT"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Where is the Directorate of Higher Education located? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Dehradun", "Roorkee", "Narendra Nagar"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "The 'School Chalo' campaign is for children between which ages? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": [
          "3 to 7 years",
          "5 to 10 years",
          "6 to 12 years",
          "6 to 14 years"
        ],
        "answer": "6 to 14 years"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Where is the State Educational Research and Training Institute located? (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": ["Bhimtal", "Narendra Nagar", "Ghurdaur", "Srinagar"],
        "answer": "Narendra Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a dialect of Uttarakhand? (Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2016)",
        "options": ["Garhwali", "Kumaoni", "Bhojpuri", "Jaunsari"],
        "answer": "Bhojpuri"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The first agricultural university in India was established in 1960. Where is it located? (PCS Main: 2009)",
        "options": ["Faizabad", "Pantnagar", "Kanpur", "Allahabad"],
        "answer": "Pantnagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "The Garhwal Samachar newspaper is published from (PCS Main: 2009)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Kotdwar", "Pauri", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "The All India Institute of Medical Sciences is located in (PCS Main: 2003)",
        "options": ["Rishikesh", "Haridwar", "Srinagar", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Rishikesh"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Who wrote the poem 'Manoday Kavya'? (UK PCS/RO/ARO: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Man Singh",
          "Shambhu Prasad Bahuguna",
          "Gumani Pant",
          "Bhaktavi"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhaktavi"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Ayush Gram is related to (UK PCS/RO/ARO: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Yoga education",
          "Ayurvedic education",
          "Computer education",
          "Homeopathic education"
        ],
        "answer": "Ayurvedic education"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Himalayan History - Dr. Ajay Rawat",
          "Mussoorie Medley - Shro, Ganesh Shaili",
          "Himagiri Travels - Jodh Singh Negi",
          "Holi Himalay - E. Sergan Oakley"
        ],
        "answer": "Himalayan History - Dr. Ajay Rawat"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Which university in Uttarakhand was granted central university status in 2009? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "S.N.B. Garhwal University",
          "Doon University",
          "Kumaon University",
          "G.M. Pant Agricultural University"
        ],
        "answer": "S.N.B. Garhwal University"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Vishal Kirti - Pauri",
          "Swadhin Praja - Nainital",
          "Samata - Tehri",
          "Garhwali - Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "Swadhin Praja - Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "The first engineering college in Asia was established in (PCS Main: 2009)",
        "options": ["Petran", "Bangalore", "Roorkee", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Roorkee"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (PCS Main: 2010)",
        "options": [
          "Mukundilal - Tarun Kumaon",
          "Victor Mohan Joshi - Swadhin Praja",
          "Govind Vanarbh Pant - Prajavandhu",
          "Bhakta Darshan - Karmabhoomi"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Vanarbh Pant - Prajavandhu"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "The book 'Garhwal Ancient and Modern' was written by (PCS Pre: 2004, Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": ["S.P. Dabral", "A. Parmar", "G.C. Pandey", "Patiram"],
        "answer": "Patiram"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "The H.N.V. Garhwal University was granted central university status in (Lecturer: 2009)",
        "options": [
          "January 15, 2009",
          "August 15, 2009",
          "March 15, 2009",
          "January 26, 2009"
        ],
        "answer": "January 15, 2009"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "The author of the famous book 'Mussoorie Medley' is (PCS Main: 2010)",
        "options": [
          "Chandi Prasad Bhatt",
          "Prof. Ganesh Shaili",
          "Bandraprabha Aetwal",
          "Puran Chandra Pandey"
        ],
        "answer": "Prof. Ganesh Shaili"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (PCS Main: 2010)",
        "options": [
          "Himalayan District Gazetteers - Jodh Singh Negi",
          "Himalayan Travels - Jodh Singh Negi",
          "Garhwal Gazetteers - H.G. Walton",
          "Garhwal Ancient and Modern - Patiram"
        ],
        "answer": "Himalayan Travels - Jodh Singh Negi"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "The author of the Himalayan Gazetteer is (UK-EO/RI: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Ajay Rawat",
          "P. Barron",
          "E. Patkinson",
          "Mein Villa"
        ],
        "answer": "E. Patkinson"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "The 'Gaon Shanis Light' was established by (UK-EO/RI: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Annie Besant",
          "Salman Kardi",
          "Begam Sahab",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Annie Besant"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "The State Educational Research and Training Council was established for school education in (UK-EO/RI: 2017)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Narendra Nagar", "Srinagar", "Roorkee"],
        "answer": "Narendra Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (UK-EO/RI: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Vishal Kirti - Pauri",
          "Swadhin Praja - Nainital",
          "Samata - Tehri",
          "Garhwali - Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "Swadhin Praja - Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "The first engineering college in Asia was established in (PCS Main: 2009)",
        "options": ["Petran", "Bangalore", "Roorkee", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Roorkee"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (PCS Main: 2010)",
        "options": [
          "Mukundilal - Tarun Kumaon",
          "Victor Mohan Joshi - Swadhin Praja",
          "Govind Vanarbh Pant - Prajavandhu",
          "Bhakta Darshan - Karmabhoomi"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Vanarbh Pant - Prajavandhu"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "The author of the book 'Garhwal Ancient and Modern' is (PCS Pre: 2004, Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": ["S.P. Dabral", "A. Parmar", "G.C. Pandey", "Patiram"],
        "answer": "Patiram"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "The H.N.V. Garhwal University was granted central university status in (Lecturer: 2009)",
        "options": [
          "January 15, 2009",
          "August 15, 2009",
          "March 15, 2009",
          "January 26, 2009"
        ],
        "answer": "January 15, 2009"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "The author of the famous book 'Mussoorie Medley' is (PCS Main: 2010)",
        "options": [
          "Chandi Prasad Bhatt",
          "Prof. Ganesh Shaili",
          "Bandraprabha Aetwal",
          "Puran Chandra Pandey"
        ],
        "answer": "Prof. Ganesh Shaili"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "Gurukul Kangri Vidyalaya was established by Swami Shraddhanand in Haridwar in:",
        "options": ["1902", "1903", "1904", "1905"],
        "answer": "1902"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Devbhoomi Muskaan Yojana has been started to provide excellent education to the deprived sections of the society in:",
        "options": ["2007", "2008", "2009", "2012"],
        "answer": "2009"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "British Garhwal Gazetteer - H.G. Walton",
          "Himalayan Parichay - Rahul Sankrityayan",
          "Himalayan Travels - Jodh Singh Negi",
          "Almora Gazetteers - A.F.T. Etkinson"
        ],
        "answer": "Himalayan Parichay - Rahul Sankrityayan"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Keedapach - Uttarakhand",
          "Kumaon's Folk Art - Yashodhar Mathpal",
          "Himalayan History - Madan Chandra Bhatt",
          "Himalayan Caves - Acharya Dharmanand"
        ],
        "answer": "Himalayan Caves - Acharya Dharmanand"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs of magazines and their publication locations is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Jan - Dehradun",
          "Pahad - Nainital",
          "Aaj Ka Pahad - Pithoragarh",
          "Yugvani - Haridwar"
        ],
        "answer": "Yugvani - Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs of newspapers and their publication locations is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Uttarakhand Darpan - Dehradun",
          "Karma Bhoomi - Tehri",
          "Aniket - Gopeshwar",
          "Satyapach - Kotdwar"
        ],
        "answer": "Satyapach - Kotdwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Which of the following pairs of newspapers and their publication locations is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Doon Darpan - Dehradun",
          "Prajabandhu - Ranikhet",
          "Satyapach - Kotdwar",
          "Himavat - Lansdowne"
        ],
        "answer": "Satyapach - Kotdwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "Who among the following wrote 'Vedmala'?",
        "options": [
          "Hariram Dhasmana",
          "Bhajan Singh 'Bhajan'",
          "Satyanarayan Raturi",
          "Damodar Prasad Chapliyal"
        ],
        "answer": "Hariram Dhasmana"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "The famous poem 'Singhnad' is written by whom among the following?",
        "options": [
          "Bhajan Singh",
          "Abharam Gairola",
          "Chandramohan Raturi",
          "Bhagwati Prasad Panbri"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhajan Singh"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "The famous poem 'Utho Garhwaliyo' is written by which of the following poets?",
        "options": [
          "Satyanarayan Raturi",
          "Chandramohan Raturi",
          "Ghanshyam Raturi",
          "Satya Sharan Raturi"
        ],
        "answer": "Satyanarayan Raturi"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "From which Apabhramsa has Pahari Hindi developed?",
        "options": [
          "Brahad Apabhramsa",
          "Shaurseni Apabhramsa",
          "Khas Apabhramsa",
          "Ardhamagadhi Apabhramsa"
        ],
        "answer": "Khas Apabhramsa"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book on the 'Coolie Begar' practice in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Shekhar Pathak",
          "Barrister Mukundi Lal",
          "Tara Munshiram",
          "Chintamani Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. Shekhar Pathak"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Who is the author of the novel 'Tumhare Liye'?",
        "options": [
          "Shivani",
          "Shailesh Matiyani",
          "Manohar Shyam Joshi",
          "Himanshu Joshi"
        ],
        "answer": "Shivani"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Who is the author of the famous book 'British Kumaon Garhwal'?",
        "options": [
          "S.M. Rawat",
          "Prakash Pant",
          "Dr. R.S. Tolia",
          "Dr. Shekhar Pathak"
        ],
        "answer": "Dr. R.S. Tolia"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "Who established the Himalayan Institute Hospital and Trust?",
        "options": [
          "Narayan Dutt Tiwari",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Swami Ram",
          "Hemvati Nandan Bahuguna"
        ],
        "answer": "Swami Ram"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Garhwal Paintings'?",
        "options": ["Molaram", "Mukundi Lal", "Patiram", "H.G. Walton"],
        "answer": "Mukundi Lal"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Which of the following is the oldest university in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Kumaon University, Nainital",
          "Garhwal University, Srinagar",
          "Gurukul Kangri University, Haridwar",
          "G.B. Pant University of Agriculture and Technology, Pantnagar"
        ],
        "answer": "Gurukul Kangri University, Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Himalayan Art'?",
        "options": [
          "Dr. Kumar Swami",
          "G.C. Upreti",
          "Kishan Lal Vaidya",
          "Barrister Mukundi Lal"
        ],
        "answer": "Barrister Mukundi Lal"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "From where is the magazine 'Pahad', based on Himalayan society, culture, and environment, published?",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Champawat", "Nainital", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a state university of Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Kumaon University",
          "Shri Dev Suman University",
          "Gurukul Kangri University",
          "H.N.B. Medical University"
        ],
        "answer": "H.N.B. Medical University"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "Which university in India is considered the pioneer of the Green Revolution? (Junior Assistant: 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Indira Gandhi Agricultural University, Raipur",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant University of Agriculture and Technology, Pantnagar",
          "Chaudhary Charan Singh Agricultural University, Hisar, Haryana",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Govind Ballabh Pant University of Agriculture and Technology, Pantnagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "Who was the founder of 'The Doon School'? (Junior Assistant: 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Lal Bahadur Shastri",
          "Satish Ranjan Das",
          "Jawaharlal Nehru",
          "Rajiv Gandhi"
        ],
        "answer": "Satish Ranjan Das"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "Who is the author of the booklet 'Descriptive List of Martial Castes of Almora'? (Village Panchayat Development Officer: 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Badridutt Pandey",
          "Govind Ballabh Pant",
          "Hargovind Pant",
          "Ganga Dutt Upreti"
        ],
        "answer": "Ganga Dutt Upreti"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "Who is the author of 'British Garhwal Gazetteer'? (PRO: 2021)",
        "options": [
          "H.G. Bakalton",
          "E. Atkinson",
          "H. Moorcroft",
          "William Fraser"
        ],
        "answer": "H.G. Bakalton"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "Shiv Prasad Dabral 'Charan' is a/an (PRO: 2021)",
        "options": ["Politician", "Historian", "Painter", "Social Worker"],
        "answer": "Historian"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Holy Himalaya'? (PRO: 2021)",
        "options": [
          "Patiram",
          "E. Sherman Oakley",
          "Sarla Behn",
          "Jim Corbett"
        ],
        "answer": "E. Sherman Oakley"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "When was the 'British Garhwal Gazetteer' published? (DEO: 2021)",
        "options": ["1910 AD", "1912 AD", "1934 AD", "1916 AD"],
        "answer": "1910 AD"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "Which of the following is a sub-dialect of Garhwali? (Forest Guard: 2023)",
        "options": ["Siraali", "Kumaoni", "Nagpuriya", "Salani"],
        "answer": "Nagpuriya"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Who among the following named 'Kauravi' for 'Khariboli'? (Forest Guard: 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Suniti Kumar Chatterji",
          "Kamta Prasad Guru",
          "Rahul Sankrityayan",
          "Dr. Bholanath Tiwari"
        ],
        "answer": "Rahul Sankrityayan"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "Which of the following is a sub-dialect of 'Kumaoni'? (Patwari Lekhpal: 2023)",
        "options": ["Salani", "Khasparjia", "Nagpuriya", "Danpuria"],
        "answer": "Danpuria"
      },
      {
        "id": 61,
        "question": "Which of the following is the script of the Jaunsari language? (VDO: 2023)",
        "options": ["Brahmi", "Kharosthi", "Devanagari", "Kutil"],
        "answer": "Devanagari"
      },
      {
        "id": 63,
        "question": "In which year did the publication of the 'Garhwali' newspaper begin?",
        "options": ["1868", "1871", "1902", "1905"],
        "answer": "1905"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Economic Scenario",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "According to the statistics of 2021-22, which district has the highest number of Joint Stock Companies?",
        "options": ["Rudraprayag", "Almora", "Dehradun", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Which is the largest source of tax revenue in the state?",
        "options": [
          "Entertainment Tax",
          "Commercial Tax",
          "Stamp Duty",
          "Excise Duty"
        ],
        "answer": "Commercial Tax"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Uttarakhand was given the status of a special state from which date?",
        "options": [
          "April 1, 2001",
          "April 1, 2002",
          "April 1, 2003",
          "April 1, 2004"
        ],
        "answer": "April 1, 2001"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "What is the main objective of the 'Gyanotkarsh Yojana' being run with the cooperation of the State Bank of India in the state?",
        "options": [
          "To sanction education loans to common citizens",
          "To sanction home loans to tribes",
          "To sanction loans to permanent teachers and other employees of the Uttaranchal government for purchasing computers for personal use",
          "To sanction agricultural loans to small farmers"
        ],
        "answer": "To sanction loans to permanent teachers and other employees of the Uttaranchal government for purchasing computers for personal use"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Consider the following statements: (DAP - 2003) Statement (A): There is a lot of internal power for development in the state. Reason (R): Scientific planning and effective implementation machinery are needed for development. In the context of the above, which one of the following is correct?",
        "options": [
          "Both and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
          "Both and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
          "is correct but (R) is wrong",
          "is wrong but (R) is correct"
        ],
        "answer": "Both and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Statement (A): Uttaranchal is known for its 'Money Order Economy'. Reason (R): This indicates migration for employment. Code:",
        "options": [
          "Both and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
          "Both and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
          "is correct but (R) is wrong",
          "is wrong but (R) is correct"
        ],
        "answer": "Both and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "In which district of the state was an RBI branch opened in June 2006?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Nainital", "Roorkee"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "According to 2011, what is the total working population in the state?",
        "options": ["35.01%", "36.75%", "38.39%", "39.20%"],
        "answer": "38.39%"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "After the formation of the state, the contribution of the primary sector in the state economy is gradually...",
        "options": ["Increasing", "Decreasing", "Stable", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Decreasing"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "The contribution of the secondary sector in the state economy is gradually...",
        "options": ["Increasing", "Decreasing", "Stable", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Increasing"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "When was the State Planning Commission formed?",
        "options": [
          "November 9, 2000",
          "January 1, 2001",
          "February 28, 2001",
          "March 31, 2001"
        ],
        "answer": "March 31, 2001"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Who is the ex-officio chairman of the State Planning Commission?",
        "options": [
          "Governor",
          "Chief Minister",
          "Finance Minister",
          "Finance Secretary"
        ],
        "answer": "Chief Minister"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Who among the following was the first chairman of the State Finance Commission? (Junior Assistant - 2018)",
        "options": [
          "S.K. Sharma",
          "R.K. Dhar",
          "R.M. Tolia",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "R.M. Tolia"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "According to the 2011-12 base year report by the Central Planning Commission, what percentage of people are poor in the state?",
        "options": ["16.6%", "12.5%", "17.8%", "11.24%"],
        "answer": "11.24%"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "According to the report released by the Central Planning Commission, the urban and rural poverty is respectively...",
        "options": [
          "10.62% & 10.48%",
          "24.6% & 15.0%",
          "26.7% & 15.3%",
          "23.4% & 14.5%"
        ],
        "answer": "10.62% & 10.48%"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "The GST tax system was implemented in the state from...",
        "options": [
          "January 1, 2017",
          "April 1, 2017",
          "July 1, 2017",
          "August 1, 2017"
        ],
        "answer": "July 1, 2017"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a major source for the Uttarakhand economy? (Patwari/Lekhpal - 16.23)",
        "options": ["Forest Wealth", "Tourism", "Film Industry", "Mines"],
        "answer": "Film Industry"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "The financial year starts in Uttarakhand from...",
        "options": ["January 1", "April 1", "July 1", "March 1"],
        "answer": "April 1"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "What is the main source of livelihood for the rural population in the hilly region of Uttarakhand? (UK PCS, RO/ARO - 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Horticulture",
          "Horticulture and Tourism",
          "Agriculture and Animal Husbandry",
          "Agriculture and Trade"
        ],
        "answer": "Agriculture and Animal Husbandry"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Which raw material is used to produce the handicraft item 'Mosta' in the state?",
        "options": [
          "Bamboo",
          "Hingal (Cane)",
          "Pine tree bark",
          "Pangar tree wood"
        ],
        "answer": "Hingal (Cane)"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "How was trade conducted in the state before independence? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": [
          "Through fairs",
          "Through exhibitions",
          "Through intermediaries",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Where is the largest paper factory located in the state? (PCS Main - 2006 & Upper Private Secretary, 2017)",
        "options": ["Lalkuan", "Khatima", "Haridwar", "Chakrata"],
        "answer": "Lalkuan"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "In which of the following places in the state is the 'Kattha Factory' located? (PCS Main - 2006 & Junior Clerk, 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Nainidanda - Pauri Garhwal",
          "Haldwani - Nainital",
          "Lachhiwala - Dehradun",
          "Bahadrabad - Haridwar"
        ],
        "answer": "Haldwani - Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Which place, located at a distance of 165 km from Pithoragarh, is known for woollen goods (shawls, carpets, blankets, pankhi, pashmina shawls, etc.)? (PCS Main, 2003)",
        "options": ["Gwaldam", "Joshimath", "Munsiyari", "Mana"],
        "answer": "Munsiyari"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "At the time of the creation of Uttarakhand state, the 'Eleventh Finance Commission' gave it the status of which of the following states? (PCS Pre, 2004)",
        "options": [
          "Poor Hilly State",
          "Underdeveloped State",
          "Special Category State",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Special Category State"
      },

      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Most of the paper mills in the state are located in:",
        "options": ["Nainital", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Dehradun", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Udham Singh Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "The first factory of magnesite in the state was established in: (APO - 2021)",
        "options": ["Ramgarh", "Mangolihat", "Chamba", "Shiroli"],
        "answer": "Shiroli"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Which place is known for the catechu (Katha) industry?",
        "options": ["Kashipur", "Haldwani", "Haridwar", "Pauri"],
        "answer": "Haldwani"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "The RBI branch in Dehradun was established in:",
        "options": ["June 2004", "June 2005", "June 2006", "June 2007"],
        "answer": "June 2006"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "The oldest cotton textile mill in the state is in:",
        "options": ["Roorkee", "Rudrapur", "Kashipur", "Sitarganj"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "The Special Integrated Industrial Promotion Policy for hilly and remote areas in the state was implemented on April 1, 2008. This policy will remain in effect until: (PCS Main, 2010)",
        "options": [
          "March 31, 2018",
          "March 31, 2015",
          "March 31, 2020",
          "March 31, 2028"
        ],
        "answer": "March 31, 2018"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Which of the following industrial areas is developed by SIDCOL? (Group 'C' - 2011)",
        "options": ["Pantnagar", "Kotdwar", "Haridwar", "Kashipur"],
        "answer": "Pantnagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Where is Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL) located? (Office Assistant - 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Ranibagh (Nainital)",
          "Ranipur (Haridwar)",
          "Ranipokhari",
          "Ranikhet (Almora)"
        ],
        "answer": "Ranipur (Haridwar)"
      },
      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "The unit of Hindustan Machine Tools is located at which of the following places? (Female Sub-Inspector - 2016)",
        "options": ["Ranibagh (Nainital)", "Ranipur", "Almora", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Ranibagh (Nainital)"
      },
      {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "At which place is the cement factory established?",
        "options": ["Ranibagh", "Ranipur", "Ranipokhari", "Ranikhet"],
        "answer": "Ranipokhari"
      },
      {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "At which place is the Cooperative Drugs Factory established?",
        "options": ["Ranibagh", "Ranipur", "Ranipokhari", "Ranikhet"],
        "answer": "Ranikhet"
      },
      {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "Most of the cement factories in the state are concentrated in:",
        "options": ["Haridwar", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Dehradun", "Nainital"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Which of the following industries and places is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Hindustan Antibiotics - Rishikesh",
          "Ordnance Factory - Raipur",
          "Electronics Industry - Lansdowne",
          "Benzene Factory - Ranikhet"
        ],
        "answer": "Benzene Factory - Ranikhet"
      },
      {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Which of the following industries and places is not correctly matched?",
        "options": [
          "Woollen Textile Industry - Nainital",
          "Carpet Industry - Pithoragarh",
          "Copper Industry - Almora",
          "Catechu Industry - Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "Catechu Industry - Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "The Craft Design Center for the development of handicrafts and handlooms has been established at:",
        "options": ["Kashipur", "Shyampur", "Haldwani", "Selakui"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },
      {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "The Silk Park is being established in the state at:",
        "options": ["Rudrapur", "Dehradun", "Roorkee", "Haldwani"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Which district is most prominent for making sports goods in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": ["Almora", "Haridwar", "Bageshwar", "Nainital"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Which place in Uttarakhand is being developed as 'Brass City'? (Review Officer - 2016)",
        "options": ["Bazpur", "Rudrapur", "Pithoragarh", "Almora"],
        "answer": "Almora"
      },
      {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "What is the use of 'Ringal' in Uttarakhand? (Forest Guard - 2016)",
        "options": [
          "In bangles",
          "In blankets",
          "In pearl necklaces",
          "In carpets, bowls, baskets"
        ],
        "answer": "In carpets, bowls, baskets"
      },
      {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "In the budgetary announcement for the financial year 2023-24, which district was announced to have a state-run old age home established?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Almora", "Nainital", "Udham Singh Nagar"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Which of the following places is not related to SIDCUL (State Infrastructure and Industrial Development Corporation of Uttarakhand)? (PCS - 2023)",
        "options": ["Roorkee", "Selakui", "Sitarganj", "Haridwar"],
        "answer": "Roorkee"
      },
      {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Which of the following establishments is not located in Uttarakhand? (PCS - 2023)",
        "options": ["CBRI", "ONGC", "HAL", "BHEL"],
        "answer": "HAL"
      },
      {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Which type of banks had the minimum number in Uttarakhand in the year 2020-21? (PCS - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Nationalized Banks",
          "Regional Banks",
          "Private Banks",
          "District Cooperative Banks"
        ],
        "answer": "District Cooperative Banks"
      },
      {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "In which year was VAT (Value Added Tax) implemented in Uttarakhand? (PCS - 22, 23)",
        "options": ["2007", "2010", "2012", "2005"],
        "answer": "2005"
      },
      {
        "id": 51,
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey 2021-22, what was the average monthly per capita expenditure in rural areas in 2011-12? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["₹1520", "₹1726", "₹1850", "₹1975"],
        "answer": "₹1726"
      },
      {
        "id": 52,
        "question": "What is the contribution of the tertiary sector to Uttarakhand's economy at current prices in the year 2021-22? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["42.92%", "12.11%", "44.98%", "55.52%"],
        "answer": "55.52%"
      },
      {
        "id": 53,
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey 2021-22, what was the unemployment rate (15 years and above) in Uttarakhand in 2019-20? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["6.1%", "6.6%", "7.1%", "8.2%"],
        "answer": "6.6%"
      },
      {
        "id": 54,
        "question": "What is the maximum limit of subsidy given to women entrepreneurs in the micro, small, and medium enterprise sector in Uttarakhand in 2015? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["₹12.5 lakh", "₹20 lakh", "₹25 lakh", "₹32 lakh"],
        "answer": "₹25 lakh"
      },
      {
        "id": 55,
        "question": "What was the fish production in Uttarakhand in 2021-22? (Forest Guard - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "5.130 thousand metric tons",
          "5.367 thousand metric tons",
          "6.090 thousand metric tons",
          "7.900 thousand metric tons"
        ],
        "answer": "6.090 thousand metric tons"
      },
      {
        "id": 56,
        "question": "By what brand name are the handicrafts of Uttarakhand sold in other states of India? (Forest Guard - 2021)",
        "options": [
          "Dev Bhoomi Brand",
          "Himalayan Brand",
          "Uttarakhandi Brand",
          "Himadri Brand"
        ],
        "answer": "Himadri Brand"
      },
      {
        "id": 57,
        "question": "According to the Sixth Economic Census of Uttarakhand 2012-13, which district of Uttarakhand has the least number of enterprises operated by women entrepreneurs? (Forest Guard - 2021)",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Rudraprayag", "Pithoragarh"],
        "answer": "Rudraprayag"
      },
      {
        "id": 58,
        "question": "According to the Uttarakhand Economic Survey 2021-22, what was the main export item of Uttarakhand till December 2021 (during 2021-22)? (Forest Guard - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Plastic and Rubber",
          "Chemical Products",
          "Base Metals",
          "Gems, Precious and Semi-Precious Stones"
        ],
        "answer": "Chemical Products"
      },
      {
        "id": 59,
        "question": "Based on the year 2020-21 (Revised Budget Estimates), from which item did the Uttarakhand government receive the maximum revenue? (Patwari Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Direct and Indirect Taxes",
          "Interest and Property Receipts",
          "Revenue Grants from the Government of India",
          "Other Revenue Receipts"
        ],
        "answer": "Revenue Grants from the Government of India"
      },
      {
        "id": 60,
        "question": "When was the 'One District Two Products Scheme' implemented in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "October 2020",
          "January 2021",
          "October 2021",
          "April 2022"
        ],
        "answer": "October 2021"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Welfare Schemes and Other Programs",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "When was the new youth policy promulgated in the state?",
        "options": ["2001", "2005", "2010", "2023"],
        "answer": "2023"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "What percentage of reservation for women is provided in panchayats and forest panchayats?",
        "options": ["33%", "25%", "50%", "40%"],
        "answer": "50%"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "What percentage of reservation is provided for differently-abled people in government services? (Group 'C' - 2011)",
        "options": ["2%", "3%", "4%", "5%"],
        "answer": "4%"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "When was the emergency medical service scheme 108 launched in the state?",
        "options": ["2005", "2007", "2008", "2010"],
        "answer": "2008"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "The Chief Minister Mahalakshmi scheme is related to which of the following?",
        "options": [
          "Differently-abled people",
          "Youths",
          "Women",
          "Ex-servicemen"
        ],
        "answer": "Women"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "The Pradhan Mantri Matru Vandana Yojana is related to which of the following?",
        "options": [
          "Ex-servicemen",
          "State agitators",
          "Pregnant women",
          "Women"
        ],
        "answer": "Pregnant women"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Which year was declared as the Women Empowerment Year by the state government?",
        "options": ["2005-06", "2006-07", "2007-08", "2008-09"],
        "answer": "2006-07"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The Chief Minister Dal Poshit Yojana is operational in the state from:",
        "options": [
          "September 11, 2019",
          "September 12, 2019",
          "September 14, 2019",
          "September 15, 2019"
        ],
        "answer": "September 12, 2019"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "When was the Atal Ayushman Uttarakhand Yojana implemented in the state?",
        "options": ["2015", "2016", "2017", "2018"],
        "answer": "2018"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "The 108 emergency medical service is named after whom? (Group 'C' - 2011)",
        "options": [
          "Pt. Deen Dayal Upadhyay",
          "Shyama Prasad Mukherjee",
          "Atal Bihari Vajpayee",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Atal Bihari Vajpayee"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "The JICA project in the state is being run with the cooperation of which country?",
        "options": ["Britain", "America", "Japan", "Central Government"],
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "The Maulana Azad Education Finance Foundation scheme is for which of the following?",
        "options": [
          "Women",
          "Differently-abled people",
          "Minorities",
          "Elderly people"
        ],
        "answer": "Minorities"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "How much pension is given per month for the maintenance of elderly people?",
        "options": ["₹500", "₹800", "₹1000", "₹1500"],
        "answer": "₹1500"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "What percentage of reservation is provided to ex-servicemen in Group 'C' and 'D' services of the state?",
        "options": ["3%", "4%", "5%", "7%"],
        "answer": "5%"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "How much pension is given per month for the maintenance of differently-abled people?",
        "options": ["₹400", "₹500", "₹800", "₹1200"],
        "answer": "₹1200"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "In which districts of Uttarakhand is the 'Minor Girl Scheme' running?",
        "options": [
          "Haridwar and Dehradun",
          "Haridwar and Nainital",
          "Haridwar and Udham Singh Nagar",
          "Dehradun and Nainital"
        ],
        "answer": "Haridwar and Udham Singh Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "When was the Rural Development Agency established?",
        "options": ["2017", "2018", "2019", "2020"],
        "answer": "2018"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "The 'Ustad' scheme is related to:",
        "options": ["Women", "Minorities", "Youths", "Scheduled Tribes"],
        "answer": "Minorities"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "When was the Chief Minister Vatsalya Yojana started?",
        "options": [
          "August 14, 2021",
          "August 15, 2021",
          "August 3, 2021",
          "August 2, 2021"
        ],
        "answer": "August 3, 2021"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "The 'Shree Ann Solar Self-Employment Scheme' is for whom?",
        "options": ["Youths", "Soldiers", "Elderly people", "Children"],
        "answer": "Youths"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "The Chief Minister 'Aanchal Amrit Yojana' is running in the state for:",
        "options": [
          "Training and nutrition of girls",
          "Protection of girls' rights",
          "Protection of girls from trafficking",
          "Providing milk to children aged 3 to 6 years"
        ],
        "answer": "Providing milk to children aged 3 to 6 years"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "For what purpose was the 'Mission Gaura Shakti' launched in 2021?",
        "options": [
          "To empower the economic status of women",
          "For the safety, empowerment of women, and prevention of violence against them",
          "To strengthen the political participation of women",
          "To strengthen the health status of women"
        ],
        "answer": "For the safety, empowerment of women, and prevention of violence against them"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "What is the revised name of the commission previously formed by the Uttarakhand government to address the problem of migration?",
        "options": [
          "Migration Commission",
          "Rural Development and Migration Prevention Commission",
          "Rural Development and Migration Commission",
          "Rural Development, Migration, and Panchayati Raj Commission"
        ],
        "answer": "Rural Development, Migration, and Panchayati Raj Commission"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "How much amount is given under the Uttarakhand government's 'Vatsalya Yojana'?",
        "options": ["₹5,000", "₹2,000", "₹3,000", "₹1,500"],
        "answer": "₹3,000"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Which of the following is not related to the objectives of 'Gramya-I'?",
        "options": [
          "Improving the potential productivity of natural resources",
          "Increasing the income of rural residents",
          "Environmental sustainability approach",
          "Increasing the productivity of rain-fed agriculture"
        ],
        "answer": "Environmental sustainability approach"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "In which districts of Uttarakhand has the 'Minor Girl Scheme' been started?",
        "options": [
          "Haridwar and Dehradun",
          "Haridwar and Nainital",
          "Haridwar and Udham Singh Nagar",
          "Dehradun and Nainital"
        ],
        "answer": "Haridwar and Udham Singh Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "The Uttarakhand Start-up Policy 2023 has been launched for:",
        "options": [
          "To promote entrepreneurship in education",
          "To commercialize innovation in educational institutions",
          "To encourage entrepreneurship among women",
          "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "The Char Dham project running in Uttarakhand is related to which work?",
        "options": [
          "Maintenance of temples",
          "Road construction",
          "Pollution control",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Road construction"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is not correct in the context of Uttarakhand's 'Deendayal Upadhyay Home Stay Development Scheme'?",
        "options": [
          "This scheme was started in 2017",
          "Under this scheme, a 50% (maximum ₹15 lakh) grant is given by the department in hilly areas",
          "Under this scheme, a 25% (maximum ₹7.5 lakh) grant is given by the tourism department in plain areas",
          "The objective of this scheme is to improve the economic status of local people by providing self-employment"
        ],
        "answer": "This scheme was started in 2017"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "The 'Char Dham' (Gangotri, Yamunotri, Badrinath, and Kedarnath) of Uttarakhand are located in which group of districts?",
        "options": [
          "Uttarkashi - Chamoli - Tehri",
          "Uttarkashi - Tehri - Pauri",
          "Uttarkashi - Rudraprayag - Tehri",
          "Uttarkashi - Rudraprayag - Chamoli"
        ],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi - Rudraprayag - Chamoli"
      },
      {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "Which of the following is the nodal department for the operation of the Pradhan Mantri Kisan Samman Nidhi Yojana in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Agriculture Department",
          "Labor Department",
          "Planning Department",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Agriculture Department"
      },
      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "The 'Char Dham' project running in Uttarakhand is related to which of the following works?",
        "options": [
          "Road construction",
          "Maintenance of temples",
          "Pollution control",
          "Cleaning of urban areas"
        ],
        "answer": "Road construction"
      },
      {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Who is appointed as the nodal officer for the operation of the 'Pradhan Mantri Kisan Samman Nidhi Yojana' in Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
          "Commissioner and Secretary, Revenue Council",
          "Commissioner, Finance Department",
          "Principal Secretary",
          "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Commissioner and Secretary, Revenue Council"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Energy Resources",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "The 16 km long underground tunnel built to carry water for the Joshimath to Dharasu hydroelectric project is located on which river? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": [
          "Dhauli River",
          "Sarada River",
          "Bhagirathi River",
          "Alaknanda River"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi River"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "How much electricity is received as royalty from hydroelectric projects established by other states or the central government in the state?",
        "options": ["15%", "12%", "18%", "11%"],
        "answer": "12%"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "In which district of Uttarakhand is the 'Kishau Dam' located? (Female Sub-Inspector - 2016)",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Chamoli", "Dehradun", "None of these"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "India has the Mahakali River Treaty with which other country? (PCS Main - 2001)",
        "options": ["Pakistan", "Sri Lanka", "Nepal", "Bangladesh"],
        "answer": "Nepal"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of Uttarakhand Renewable Energy Development Agency (UREDA)?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Almora", "Pauri", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Tehri Dam is the fourth highest dam in the world, while in Asia it is the:",
        "options": ["Second", "First", "Third", "Eighth"],
        "answer": "First"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "The Koteshwar Dam is being built on which river? (PCS Main - 2001)",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Dhauliganga", "Bhagirathi", "Birahi Ganga"],
        "answer": "Bhagirathi"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The first phase of the 1000 MW Tehri project was commissioned in: (Junior Assistant - 2018)",
        "options": ["2007", "2008", "2009", "2010"],
        "answer": "2007"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "The area of Tehri Reservoir (Swami Ramtirtha Sagar) is:",
        "options": [
          "42 square km",
          "48 square km",
          "345 square km",
          "480 square km"
        ],
        "answer": "42 square km"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Under the State Energy Policy, projects up to how many megawatts are placed in the small project category?",
        "options": ["15 MW", "25 MW", "35 MW", "30 MW"],
        "answer": "25 MW"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "The state-level energy park is located in: (Forest Guard - 2016)",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Nainital", "Udham Singh Nagar"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "In which district is 'Nanak Sagar' located? (Forest Guard - 2016)",
        "options": ["Almora", "Pauri", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Chamoli"],
        "answer": "Udham Singh Nagar"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched? (Village Panchayat Development Officer - 2018)",
        "options": [
          "Tehari Nagpala Project - Uttarkashi",
          "Vishnuprayag Project - Rudraprayag",
          "Maneri Bhali Project - Uttarkashi",
          "Saptever Project - Pithoragarh"
        ],
        "answer": "Vishnuprayag Project - Rudraprayag"
      },
      {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "In which year was the agreement with Russia signed for cooperation in the Tehri project?",
        "options": ["1975", "1972", "1986", "1980"],
        "answer": "1986"
      },
      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "The Uttarakhand government's 400 MW Vishnuprayag hydroelectric project is located on which river in Chamoli district?",
        "options": ["Mandakini", "Alaknanda", "Pindar", "Mandakini"],
        "answer": "Alaknanda"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "The first hydroelectric project in the state and North India was built in:",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Haridwar", "Nainital", "Tehri"],
        "answer": "Dehradun"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "The artificial lake with the highest capacity in the state is located in:",
        "options": ["Tehri", "Kalagarh", "Kotar", "Lakhwad"],
        "answer": "Tehri"
      },
      {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "The largest hydroelectric project in the state is: (Lecturer - 2009 & Village Panchayat Officer - 2016, RO/ARO - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Kotli Bhel Hydroelectric Project",
          "Vishnuprayag Hydroelectric Project",
          "Tehri Hydroelectric Project",
          "Maneri Bhali Hydroelectric Project"
        ],
        "answer": "Tehri Hydroelectric Project"
      },
      {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "The Uttarakhand Jal Vidyut Nigam was established in: (Junior Assistant - 2017)",
        "options": [
          "February 9, 2001",
          "February 10, 2001",
          "February 11, 2001",
          "February 12, 2001"
        ],
        "answer": "February 12, 2001"
      },
      {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "The first hydroelectric project in the state is: (Village Development Officer - 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Dhakpathar Hydroelectric Project",
          "Maneri Bhali Hydroelectric Project",
          "Dhauliganga Hydroelectric Project",
          "Glogi Hydroelectric Project"
        ],
        "answer": "Glogi Hydroelectric Project"
      },
      {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "The highest dam in Uttarakhand is: (Female Constable - 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Koteshwar Dam",
          "Nanak Sagar Dam",
          "Tehri Dam",
          "Jamrani Dam"
        ],
        "answer": "Tehri Dam"
      },
      {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Select the incorrect pair: (Revenue Inspector - 2017)",
        "options": [
          "Tehri Dam - Bhagirathi and Bhilangana Rivers",
          "Kishau Dam - Tons River",
          "Koteshwar Dam - Saryu River",
          "Lakhwad Dam - Yamuna River"
        ],
        "answer": "Koteshwar Dam - Saryu River"
      },
      {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "When was the 'Tehri Hydroelectric Development Corporation' established? (Junior Assistant - 2017)",
        "options": ["1965", "1977", "1980", "1988"],
        "answer": "1988"
      },
      {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "The largest water project in the state is: (PCS Pre - 2016)",
        "options": [
          "Tehri Project",
          "Khadodi Project",
          "Pathri Project",
          "Sharda Project"
        ],
        "answer": "Tehri Project"
      },
      {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "The 'Vishnugarh Pipalkoti Hydroelectric Project' is being developed on which of the following rivers?",
        "options": ["Ganga", "Yamuna", "Sabarmati", "Alaknanda"],
        "answer": "Alaknanda"
      },
      {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "What is the height of the Tehri Dam? (Enforcement Constable - 2011)",
        "options": [
          "240.2 meters",
          "240.5 meters",
          "235.5 meters",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "240.5 meters"
      },
      {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "The Uttasu Hydroelectric Project is located on which river? (DEO - 2011)",
        "options": ["Alaknanda", "Bhagirathi", "Kali", "None of the above"],
        "answer": "Alaknanda"
      },
      {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "In which district is the Maneri Bhali Project located? (Patwari Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": ["Tehri", "Dehradun", "Pithoragarh", "Uttarkashi"],
        "answer": "Uttarkashi"
      },
      {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "In which district is the Jamrani Dam located? (Junior Assistant - 2023)",
        "options": ["Pithoragarh", "Dehradun", "Udham Singh Nagar", "Nainital"],
        "answer": "Nainital"
      },
      {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Who led the cycle rally from Gangasagar to Gangotri against the construction of the Tehri Dam on the Bhagirathi River? (Patwari Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": [
          "Anil Joshi",
          "Chandi Prasad Bhatt",
          "Sunderlal Bahuguna",
          "Rajendra Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "Sunderlal Bahuguna"
      },

      {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Where is the second plant for producing recycled plastic in Uttarakhand established? (Patwari Lekhpal - 2023)",
        "options": ["Lansdowne", "Kashipur", "Haridwar", "Bhimtal"],
        "answer": "Kashipur"
      },

      {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Which of the following river valley projects is related to the Tons River? (EO/RI - 2023)",
        "options": ["Deval", "Khodri", "Chilla", "Kotli-Bhel"],
        "answer": "Khodri"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chapter": "Uttarakhand: Transportation System",
    "questions": [
      {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Which is the last railway station in Uttarakhand that is useful for both Garhwal and Kumaon regions? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": ["Tanakpur", "Kotdwar", "Rishikesh", "Ramnagar"],
        "answer": "Rishikesh"
      },
      {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "The opening of the 'Kandi Marg' motor-travel route in Uttarakhand is significant because it will greatly reduce travel distance between: (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": [
          "Ramnagar and Haridwar",
          "Haldwani and Dharchula",
          "Rishikesh and Gangotri",
          "Delhi and Dehradun"
        ],
        "answer": "Ramnagar and Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "The proposed 'Himalayan Highway Project' is being implemented from:",
        "options": [
          "Munsiyari to Mana",
          "Pangu to Purola",
          "Lohaghat to Tuini",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Lohaghat to Tuini"
      },
      {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "At which place in Uttarakhand is the 'Naini Saini Airport' located? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": ["Chamoli", "Pantnagar", "Pithoragarh", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Which place is at the shortest distance from Kailash Mansarovar (China) in Uttarakhand? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": [
          "Narayan Ashram",
          "Mayawati Ashram",
          "Anasakti Ashram",
          "Tawaghat"
        ],
        "answer": "Tawaghat"
      },
      {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "How many national highways were there in the state by the end of 2021?",
        "options": ["5", "7", "9", "22"],
        "answer": "7"
      },
      {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "What is the longest national highway in the state?",
        "options": ["7", "34", "109", "74"],
        "answer": "7"
      },
      {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "The Badrinath temple is located on which national highway?",
        "options": ["7", "34", "109", "107"],
        "answer": "7"
      },
      {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Gaurikund (Kedarnath) is located on which national highway?",
        "options": ["107", "109", "58", "7"],
        "answer": "107"
      },
      {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Gangotri is located on which national highway?",
        "options": ["34", "7", "109", "707A"],
        "answer": "34"
      },
      {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Yamunotri is located on which national highway?",
        "options": ["107", "109", "58", "134"],
        "answer": "134"
      },
      {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "What is the shortest national highway in the state?",
        "options": ["34", "30", "109", "707A"],
        "answer": "707A"
      },
      {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Where is Gochar Airport located? (PCS Main - 2006)",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Chamoli", "Pithoragarh", "Pauri"],
        "answer": "Chamoli"
      },

      {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "In how many districts of the state are railway lines laid?",
        "options": ["5", "6", "7", "4"],
        "answer": "6"
      },
      {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "The first railway line in the state was built in 1884. Which was that line?",
        "options": [
          "Laksar - Haridwar",
          "Haridwar - Dehradun",
          "Haridwar - Rishikesh",
          "Kichha - Kathgodam"
        ],
        "answer": "Kichha - Kathgodam"
      },
      {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Which airport is being developed as a greenfield airport?",
        "options": ["Jolly Grant", "Naini Saini", "Phoolbagh", "Gochar"],
        "answer": "Phoolbagh"
      },
      {
        "question": "18. In which district is the highest number of railway stations located?",
        "options": ["K.M.N.", "Haridwar", "Dehradun", "Nainital"],
        "answer": "Haridwar"
      },
      {
        "question": "19. Which of the following places is not located on National Highway 109?",
        "options": ["Rudrapur", "Almora", "Kaladhungi", "Ranikhet"],
        "answer": "Kaladhungi"
      },
      {
        "question": "20. Which of the following places is not located on National Highway 7?",
        "options": ["Dehradun", "Rishikesh", "Devprayag", "Rudrapur"],
        "answer": "Rudrapur"
      },
      {
        "question": "21. Which of the following cities is not located on National Highway 9?",
        "options": ["Sitarganj", "Khatima", "Askote", "Dharchula"],
        "answer": "Askote"
      },
      {
        "question": "22. Which of the following cities is not located on National Highway 34?",
        "options": ["Gangotri", "Dharasu", "Rishikesh", "Berinag"],
        "answer": "Berinag"
      },
      {
        "question": "23. Which airport in the state has the highest number of operations? (PCS Pre - 2016)",
        "options": ["Pantnagar", "Jolly Grant (Dehradun)", "Gochar", "Bharkot"],
        "answer": "Jolly Grant (Dehradun)"
      },
      {
        "question": "24. Which of the following is not a final point of rail transport in Uttarakhand? (Review Officer - 2016)",
        "options": ["Kathgodam", "Dehradun", "Kotdwar", "Laksar"],
        "answer": "Laksar"
      },
      {
        "question": "25. In which year was the Kumaon Motor Owners Union established? (Junior Assistant - 2018)",
        "options": ["1938", "1939", "1940", "None of these"],
        "answer": "1939"
      },
      {
        "question": "26. Which is the longest national highway in Uttarakhand? (Forest Guard - 2016)",
        "options": ["NH-34", "NH-7", "NH-109", "NH-309"],
        "answer": "NH-7"
      },
      {
        "question": "27. In which district is the 'Naini Saini Airport' located? (Village Development Officer - 2014)",
        "options": ["Uttarkashi", "Pithoragarh", "Chamoli", "Dehradun"],
        "answer": "Pithoragarh"
      },
      {
        "question": "28. In which year was Dehradun connected by railway? (PRO - 2021)",
        "options": ["1910", "1900", "1890", "1885"],
        "answer": "1900"
      },
      {
        "question": "29. In which year was the 'Garhwal Motor Owners Union Limited' established? (Village Development Officer - 2021)",
        "options": ["Pauri", "Dehradun", "Kotdwar", "Kashipur"],
        "answer": "Pauri"
      },
      {
        "question": "30. To address the problems of whom did Uttarakhand Chief Minister Shri Pushkar Singh Dhami recently inaugurate the innovative 'Pad Reporting App'? (Assistant Engineer - 2021)",
        "options": ["Schools", "Forests", "Roads", "Rivers"],
        "answer": "Roads"
      }
    ]
  }
]
